The science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport, play, and
life. Welcome to
Perform. I'm Dr. Andy Galpin. I'm a
professor and scientist and the
executive director of the human
performance center at Parker University.
And today we're going to be talking
about how to control your nervous
system. My favorite example of this
actually comes from a TV show. Many of
you probably remember the show The
Office, at least the American version.
And I'll never forget one of the classic
scenes, one of the characters, Dwight
Trroo, was telling and bragging actually
about how he had superior genes and he
was able to at his own will raise his
blood cholesterol levels. And of course,
the bewildered friends of his asked him
like, "Why would you even want to do
that?" And his response in classic
Dwight fashion was so that he could
lower his cholesterol. That had made me
laugh and I've never stopped laughing at
that. And it highlights one example,
albeit admittedly uh not sure why you
would want to do that or if that's real
or not, but it highlights the point of
how can we actually have control over
aspects of our physiology that most
people think we can't. Maybe we have
some control, but it's subconscious or
otherwise. And that's what I'm referring
to when I say control your nervous
system. There is actually a bunch of
science behind this. Probably the most
famous initial scientifically documented
experiment came in 1970. There was a
famous gentleman I think his name is
Swami Rama. I hope I pronounced that uh
appropriately. But Swami was able to do
a host of feats that still baffle most
of us. What eventually happened was he
sat in a room with a handful of
scientists and they placed what are
called ECGs to measure electrical
conductivity of his heart as well as
EEGs to measure directly into his brain.
and he performed again this whole host
of insane physiological feats without
moving. Now, that part's critical,
right? So, when he did things like take
his resting heart rate from 70 beats per
minute to reportedly 300 beats per
minute and he held that for several
seconds and then brought it back down,
he did that not by running sprints up a
hill or anything, but by just simply
sitting there and having the conscious
ability to control that aspect of his
physiology. Another really impressive
thing Swami was able to do was actually
shock the scientific team. They thought
he was in cardiac arrest because his ECG
stopped working. And what happened was
he was able to bring his heart rate
below 20 beats per minute at the same
time, give himself what's called Aphib.
And so the the machine itself thought
his heart had been stopped for like 20
seconds. I guess he signaled that, you
know, I'm fine. I'm okay here. And then
eventually brought it back up. Arguably
more impressive was some of the stuff he
was able to do with his physical
temperature. So they had him on the same
hand change the temperature by I think
like six degrees Celsius uh in his same
hand again only inches away. And so
clearly demonstrating some not only
control of his whole body temperature
but extreme precision of where that
temperature was going and where it was
not. But nonetheless, that was
documented and published and again to
this day is probably one of the more
famous cases of such incredible control
of one's what's supposed to be autonomic
physiology. A decade later and I'm going
to highlight this one as well. I think
it was 1982 actually a similar thing was
done in a more extensive group. And so
what actually happened here was a paper
was published in nature. Now that's one
of the most blue ribbon highest esteem
journals in all of science and
physiology and so pre-minent journal it
was published and they looked at a bunch
of Tibetan monks that lived in the
Himalayas studying and utilizing a
practice that's called tumo tu mmo and
they were able to do a bunch of similar
things that that Rammy was able to do. I
won't draw them out, but temperature
controls raising their body temperatures
by like 8° consciously without moving.
In fact, one of the things that they did
was them, they put wet sheets on top of
them and put them in very cold, if not
sub-zero conditions. And these
individuals were able to not only stay
neutral with temperature, stay neutral
with their heart rate, but they were
also able to physically dry the sheets
within like 30 to 60 minutes. And so you
can go on and on. You can probably find
many other case studies like this and
again thousands of anecdotes and other
stories throughout history. But I think
one thing that I'm trying to highlight
here that is
inarguable. There is clearly the ability
to run control over your physiology if
you really take the time and attention.
Is it tumo? Is it visualization? Well,
probably realistically we've got tons of
different options. And so what I'd like
to do today is talk about just a few of
them. What do we know? What does it mean
to control your nervous system? What can
we do? What can't we do? And then what
are a bunch of tactics and strategies so
that you can have a more resilient
nervous system. To start us off, I want
to make sure we're all on the same page
when I say nervous system. The easiest
way to conceptualize it is think about
it in two large branches. The first is
what's called the central nervous
system. This is your brain and brain
stem and spinal cord. And the second is
what's called your peripheral nervous
system. So this is everything else that
goes out and comes back to the central
nervous system. Now focusing on the
peripheral nervous system, that's where
most of the action happens. In this
case, the peripheral nervous system is
broken up into a couple of other
categories. One being what's called the
somatic system. This is what you can
actively control. We're not going to
talk about that much today. It's stuff
you already know you have control over.
What I want to focus more on is the
other branch. And that's what's called
the autonomic nervous system, the
ANS. And so within the autonomic nervous
system, we're talking about things like
the parasympathetic system. You may have
heard of that as rest and digest. There
are probably better ways we can describe
it and more interesting applications of
it. But nonetheless, we'll just keep it
simple right now and say that the
parasympathetic is rest and digest. You
also have the sympathetic. That is your
fight and flight. And so most of us stop
right there and we think, "Okay,
parasympathetic. I'm relaxed. I'm I'm
lethargic. I'm down. I'm chill. I'm zen.
Sympathetic. I'm fight. I'm flight. I'm
up. I'm focused. I'm aroused." And so on
and so forth. Reality of it is there's
probably more things like the freeze
mechanism. There's also the entic system
that happens here. This is kind of like
well specifically referring to your gut.
But for the most part, again, for the
sake of time, we're going to focus on
the interplay between the
parasympathetic and sympathetic nervous
system because that provides us the
ability to have a lot of control over
what our nervous system is doing. And as
I'll show here very soon, that has a
significant impact on how you're
looking, feeling, and performing in the
short and long term. And I'm
highlighting that because again, people
don't necessarily realize how much
control they actually have over those
systems. They are autonomic, but you
have the ability to move them up and
down. You can recalibrate them, and you
can consciously critically control them.
As I've given many examples of already,
if we were to zoom all the way out,
focusing on that autonomic nervous
system, the ultimate goal is to not have
too much time and attention spent on
this thing. If it is firing and
functioning appropriately, it's running
in the background. It is the software
that's running your computer. You don't
need to be worrying about it. It's
making your life easier and better, but
you shouldn't spend a lot of conscious
control over it. That said, sometimes it
gets a little bit out of whack and you
want to have the ability to toggle it
and recalibrate it so that you can bring
it up or back down based on a particular
thing you're trying to do. And so, all
we're talking about really in today's
episode is what happens when it gets egg
out of whack or is not as finely tuned
to a particular thing that you'd like
and what can you do about it. That is
ultimately today's version of
controlling your nervous system. Now, to
be really clear, because we could go in
a lot of different areas here, I'm also
going to qualify this talk even further.
We're not going to be talking about
stress management, emotions, or even
really mental health. In fact, I would
encourage you to go listen to a recent
episode of the Huberman Lab podcast, one
of the ones that's in the Essentials
catalog, where they break down a bunch
of different tools and tactics on
overall stress management and
neurological control. I'm not going to
cover any of those things today. We're
going an entirely separate route. I'm
also not only talking about
downregulation. I know personally for
many years I had this connotation
whenever I thought about
parasympathetic or recovery or relaxing.
I just always or breath work for that
matter. I just always thought it's all
about down down and it's not. In fact,
I'm not only going to focus exclusively
on breath work today either. We're going
to go well past those things. What I
really want to get at is again fine-tune
control, the ability to go down but also
go back up and making sure that system
is functioning how you'd like it to
function. So, what we will talk about
are of course the three eyes. If you're
new to the show, what that means is how
to investigate it, how to measure your
nervous system, what that even means,
what you should look for. The second eye
is interpret. So, how do you make sense
of, how do you judge or evaluate that
information that you got from that
previous test? And then the third one
which is intervene. What do you do about
it? What are protocols? What are tools
and technologies? What are things you
can do at home? What are things that can
be done at a higher level that will make
those positive impacts no matter which
direction you're going. So that overall
is our game plan today. Talk about how
we can control our nervous system in all
those forms and fashion. Today's episode
is sponsored by AG1. AG1 is a vitamin
mineral drink with probiotics,
prebiotics, and adaptogens. Initially, I
was extremely skeptical of AG1, as I am
with all supplement companies. But after
months of discussions with their lead
nutritional scientist and the general
team at AG1, I've been impressed by
AG1's commitment to sourcing the highest
quality ingredients and constantly
updating their formulas to have the
right ingredients in the optimal
amounts. By now, it is abundantly clear
that the gut microbiome plays a critical
role in everything from body composition
to bone health to mental health. And the
probiotics and prebiotics in AG1 help to
promote a healthy gut microbiome,
improve digestion, reduce food cravings,
and increase short- chain fatty acids,
which play a critical role in regulating
metabolism and immune responses. It's
for these reasons and many others that I
personally take AG1 almost every day.
Now, it's of course not a replacement
for eating whole healthy foods, but it
is a great way to make sure that you're
plugging in any gaps in your nutrition
to improve your energy, bolster your
immune system, and just generally help
promote a healthy gut. microbiome and
more. If you'd like to try AG1, you can
go to
drinkag1.com/perform to receive five
free travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2. Again, that's
drinkagg.com/perform to receive five
free travel packs plus a year supply of
vitamin D3 plus K2. Today's episode is
also sponsored by David. David makes
protein bars unlike any I have ever
encountered. They have an amazing 28
gram of protein, only 150 calories, and
zero gram of sugar. That's right, 28
gram of protein, and 75% of its calories
come from that protein. This is 50%
higher than the next closest protein
bar. Honestly, it's the best tasting
protein bar I've had by a mile. While I
often talk about the importance of
getting one gram of protein per pound of
body weight for things like muscle
health and recovery and the promotion of
lean body mass and satiety, the reality
is that for most people, getting that
one gram of protein per pound of body
weight is really challenging. However,
David makes that easy. Their bars taste
incredible and are each packed with 28 g
of protein. I eat one almost every day
and always have two or three in my
backpack when I'm traveling. like
literally always. It probably sounds
funny, but I eat them as dessert all the
time. When you try them, you'll know
exactly what I mean. The macronutrients,
one more time, are 28 gram of protein,
150 calories, and zero grams of sugar.
If you're interested in trying these
bars for yourself, you can go to
davidproin.com/perform. Again, that's
davidproin.com/perform. So, to start us
off, let's remember the ultimate goal.
We would like number one that system to
be operating independent of us. We want
it to be that software that's running.
And then two, we want to have some
active control over it when we'd like,
but we don't want to be spending our
entire day man mitigating and managing
what's going on in our aonomic nervous
system. So that goal is important
because it lays the foundation of what
we're trying to do. And so really, you
can bucket control of the system into
two main areas. Number one is what we
simply call read. All right? You need to
be able to read your current state. You
can use this with technology. So you can
buy something or use something that
tells you what's happening in your own
internal physiology or you can learn
what's called interosception or
introsception which means you can feel
it yourself. Now some people are really
good at that. Some people are completely
terrible at it. But either way we've got
to figure out what you where you
currently are. The second then step is
to regulate. So know where I'm at.
Number one. Number two move it. And when
I say regulate, I'm going to break
today's discussion up into two parts.
What I call acute things that move it
right now. So you're feeling flustered
right now. What can you do about it in
this second? Or you're feeling tired
right now. You're losing focus right
now. What are tips and tricks we can do
that'll instantly change my state? And
then the chronic ones are ones I refer
to of what are going to move the
baseline
permanently. Where we get confusion or
oftent times people that have tried
things like this where they've maybe
been disappointed in the past is they're
using things that are an acute stimuli
and hoping it makes a chronic or
permanent change. I'm really hopeful by
the end of today's talk that you'll
understand the difference and you can
use the ones in the right form and
fashion appropriately. But that's what
we're after. In either case, what we're
really trying to do is make sure that
we're widening the range of our
sympathetic and parasympathetic
experience rather than sensitizing it.
What do I mean by that? It's not about
just reducing stress. It's not about
just
downregulating. It's the opposite. In
fact, maybe not the opposite, but it is
complimentary. The analogy I like to
give here is imagine driving down a road
and you're going down a one-lane
highway. It's very likely for you to hit
the guardrails on one side of the road
when another car comes by because
there's just not a lot of room to work.
But if you expanded that highway from a
onelane road to a seven lane road,
you're far less likely to hit the
guardrails. That's what I mean. When we
become overly sensitized to the down
regulation or the upregulation, we're
driving on a onelane highway. We want to
not only become better drivers, right? I
want you to have more control so you're
not weaving as much. That alone will
help you reduce your likelihood of
hitting the wall, but mostly what we're
after is widening out that lane, giving
you seven lanes so that when you do lose
a little bit of control, you can feel
it, see it, but you're not smashing up
against walls. When I teach this, I like
to use that highway analogy. That said,
if you were to look at the research or
talk to clinicians that work in this
space, you're generally going to see it
described more as resilience. And what
that means is you have the ability to
experience high and low levels of
changes in your autonomic nervous system
without it having a dramatic impact on
your lived experience. Whether this is
your psychology, your happiness, your
anxiety, your depression, your perceived
stress load, or your actual physiology,
your hormone health, your energy, your
metabolism, your sleep, your recovery,
your physical performance. We want you
to all to be able to live a life that is
your best. Meaning, you can handle
things that challenge and change your
body from a psychological perspective or
a physiological perspective. And those
things don't have dramatic consequences
for you in the short or long term. So I
feel comfortable in saying that most of
us are better off with a more resilient
rather than sensitive nervous system.
What does that technically and
practically look like? I will give you
some tangible examples a little bit
later. But one thing you want to think
about here is if you are somebody who
feels like you are on constant
sympathetic drive, you work out really
hard at high intensity. you have a high
stress personal life, a high stress
place that you live, personal uh
experiences, jobs, so on and so forth,
then you might need to just focus on
downregulation. That's fine. We have
hundreds of randomized control trials on
people only doing downregulation work
and it creating tons of positive
experiences in their life. We've done
this a bunch in my coaching programs.
I've done this with my clients and
athletes. No question that works there.
But that's a little bit different and
not always the best scenario when
somebody's having issues on both sides,
upregulation and downregulation because
what can happen is if you're only ever
paying attention to that down regulation
size, that highway starts to get
smaller. All right? And so what you
probably want to do and if you actually
look at the research in this space more
carefully a lot of the
interventions strategically implement
both upregulation and down reggulation.
Even if somebody is highly stressed, has
a lot of anxiety or has other markers of
overall dysfunction or problems in the
nervous system, you're going to see
careful integration of both upregulation
and down reggulation. And that's because
it works like a hormatic stressor. I've
talked about this for many, many, many
years. It's one of my favorite things to
talk about. But effectively, what you're
doing is you want yourself to
downregulate. Well, just telling
yourself to calm down doesn't always
work very well. Sometimes the easiest
way to calm down is to actually give
yourself a supercharge up so that your
body naturally swings back down as an
equal and opposite reaction and the
other way. So that is the framework with
what we're going to talk about. Let's
get right into how we measure our
nervous system, what tools we can use,
and then we'll go into evaluation and
interpretations from there. With that
all in mind, let's dive into our first
eye, which is investigate. How do you
measure this stuff? Well, there's no one
answer here. I think it's easiest to
describe this in three major categories.
First one are what I call
performance-based tests. So, in the
sporting world, you'll see groups do
this where they'll take a vertical jump
test every day. So you'll come in and
every single day you'll do say three or
four maximum effort vertical jumps and
they look at the change. The assumption
there being if your vertical jump is
much lower today than it normally is
then there's a strong likelihood your
nervous system is a little bit fatigued.
That is a very common and classic uh
approach in the sport performance world.
Others do it with things like grip
strength. Again simple test, easy to do.
Uh there are reaction time drills.
There's a ton of different apps and and
low or free, you know, fairly
inexpensive technologies to look at
firing rates, uh fingering tap tests. Um
how quickly can you move your thumb?
Lots and lots of different technologies
here. Others I've seen, and we've
actually explored this a lot, have
looked at things like range of motion
and flexibility. And I've actually
personally seen this one land pretty
well. So, a basic sit and reach test of
your hamstrings and low back. A
rotational test, um, a a forearm or or
flexion extension test. I've seen all
these in the field, a ton, and I'll be
totally honest with you, they're pretty
good. We spent many years, probably over
four years, testing some of these things
every single day. We stuck them directly
up against other more scientifically
validated measures and they all came in
pretty much the same. And so these are
absolutely fine ways to measure it. It's
obviously mostly used in again the sport
performance world and so they are
hedging towards the performance aspect.
If you're not jumping as high or moving
as well, that's what they're concerned
about. A totally different approach to
this is more of a psychological
assessment. Again, you'll see research
and I've seen now huge databases. You're
talking about millions of data points
stacked directly up against something
like
mood. How you feel today? And you'll be
stunned. Stunned. On aggregate in large
populations, mood is a very strong
predictor of overall nervous system
state. How tired are you? So, fatigue is
another question. One we see often is
called RPE. a rate of perceived
exertion. Just different ways to ask
about how do you feel today? What's your
effort feel like today? How interested
in training are you today? Tons of
different questions there. That's hedged
more towards your subjective experience
where the previous ones are obviously
looking at objective performance, but
there is classic overlap between both of
them.
The third one though that is more
objective and where the bulk of the
published researches, which doesn't mean
they're better, by the way, it just
means they're more used more
scientifically, are in what I call the
physiological markers. Common ones here
are blood tests. I've spoke in season
one, we had an entire episode on
overtraining and overreaching. We also
had one on how to interpret blood tests
for high performance. In both of those,
I talked about a number of different
blood and salivary markers you can use
to assess overall fatigue and readiness
and performance. We'll have direct links
to those episodes in the show notes. You
can go check them out and see what I'm
talking about. But we're not going to
get into that stuff today because we've
we've covered a lot of it already. What
we will get into for the most part are
what I call the respiratory physiology
markers. This is everything from resting
heart rate to something called your
heart rate variability or HRV to
respiratory rate and CO2
tolerance. HRV, heart rate variability,
is the king here. Not saying it's the
best, but it has the the overwhelming
majority of the research is on
HRV. You don't see a lot anymore on
resting heart rate, and that's because
it's not very sensitive. We used to look
at it a little bit more and we kind of
walked away from it. If you get really
shot for a long time, you're overtrained
or highly chronically stressed or have a
a chronic disease, you will start to see
increases in resting heart rates that
are not being explained by a lack of
physical fitness or cardiovascular
fitness. So you can see changes in heart
rate as a result of this autonomic
nervous system being pushed into a
direction in this case more sympathetic
than you'd like. But it takes a long
time. You're not going to see the
resting heart rate move for several
weeks before you would really notice.
And then the amount of movement is
small. So it's hard to understand kind
of signal to noise ratio there. So
honestly kind of cross off resting heart
rate. Not a great marker. I don't know
too many people that use it by itself or
certainly use it as their first line of
measurement. Now, heart rate variability
is much more documented. Respiratory
rate is
growing. That's a something we're
learning much more about. And CO2
tolerance is something that I have used
a lot, but there's not a ton of research
behind that either. I will share with
you my personal experiences with all
these things, but I want to spend most
of our attention today on HRV because we
have so much more information to go off
of. So, let's dive into HRV. What is it?
Why do you care? And how do we
manipulate it? Heart rate variability is
exactly what it sounds like. It is the
variation in your heart rate. Let me use
an example. Let's say your resting heart
rate is 60 beats per minute. You would
then assume that since there's 60
seconds in one minute that your heart is
then beating in this example every
second on the second and then if you
sped your heart rate up to 670 or 80 or
90 or 100 beats per minute you would
simply shorten the time between each
heartbeat but that the time between each
heartbeat would be the same. It'd be 1
second or half a second or 3/4 of a
second or whatever the case is. Well, in
that particular case, there's no
variation in your heart rate. That's not
actually what happens. If your heart
rate is 60 beats per minute, what's
going to happen naturally is maybe it
beats at 1.1 second and then the next
beat comes at 1.2 seconds later and the
next beat after that comes 9 seconds
later, and then it comes at 08, and then
it goes to 1.3. And so there's
variations. At the end of the 60
seconds, you'll still have done 60
beats, but it won't be a metronome. It
doesn't happen every second on the
second. How variable that is is the
marker we're talking about. It's a
little bit counterintuitive, but the
more
variation, the more parasympathetic you
are. So, the more variation your heart
rate, the more downregulated. If it
becomes like a metronome, every second
on the second, it's dialed in, that
means you're in sympathetic drive. Now,
as I said, parasympathetic and
sympathetic aren't onoff switches. They
toggle back and forth. So, HRV is just
telling us kind of where at on that
entire spectrum we are.
Generally, on average here, we want to
spend more time in parasympathetic,
meaning a higher HRV, and less time in
sympathetic. Most people struggle with
spending too much time in sympathetic
and therefore have a low HRV. Now, you
can have the opposite problem, and we
have seen that. I've coached people
through that where their HRV is
extraordinarily high and they're
lethargic with no energy, no motivation,
and so on and so forth. But that's way
more rare. Generally, I would probably
say 95 times out of 100, it's the
opposite. We're getting people out of so
much time in sympathetic drive and more
in
parasympathetic. a million explanations
for this, but just as a a practical
example, you can imagine going from a a
high stress job, sitting in traffic.
Even if it's not a high stress job, but
it's a job. You're around people, you're
performing, you're in traffic, you're
listening to podcasts, you're coming
home, you're watching TV, and it's just
sensory input all the time that requires
your attention and reaction. if you're
managing children, if you're managing
other stuff, and there's just not enough
quiet time that used to be around us.
Plenty of other reasons to explain it,
but that's a it's a good way to kind of
understand the idea here of why most
people are probably in synthetic drive.
If you want to say that that means we're
in a more stressed life than we used to
be. I don't know. I'll leave that up to
you. But just from a practical
perspective, we have way more arousal
coming in way more frequently than we
probably had for most of our experience
as a human species.
So that's what HRV is. It's that
variation and that's what it tells us.
It is a snapshot into the autonomic
nervous system,
specifically parasympathetic and
sympathetic drive. It is only one
metric. It is not perfect. There's not a
single metric I will show you today that
is perfect. But it does have a lot of
research behind it. So that's roughly
what HRV is. It is at our best guess 50%
genetic and 50% lifestyle. Admittedly, I
am not thoroughly impressed with that
research. I think that number is going
to change over time, but it is
inarguable that some point of it is not
within your control, and some part of it
is. Why that matters when we get to the
interpretation stuff
later, it's not V2 max. I can't just
look at your HRV and tell you you're
good or bad. You have to consider the
fact that a large part of it is not
within your
control. Tough to interpret. The numbers
themselves aren't as specific as they
are for other variables again like V2
max. There's also a age related decline
that happens in your HRV. So it gets
lower as you age. That said, a recent
paper just came out I think actually
last year and it argued pretty strongly
that the age related decline in HRV is
not inevitable and if you maintain
function and fitness through life that
HRV should not drop as much if any uh
but certainly not as much as you think.
And so those are things that we are
learning more about but that paper just
came out first time I've seen anybody
even examine it. So we're going to have
to see where those things end up shaking
out to be. Now HRV is generally
associated with better health and you
could look at this in a variety of
different ways but from a you know
physical cardiovascular cardopulinary
fitness perspective it's generally
pretty tied. It's not perfect. Just
because V2 max goes up doesn't mean HVA
will go up and the opposite as well. So
they are related but they're definitely
not a one toone correlation and it's I'd
say a moderate correlation. So much so
we basically factor them in
independently. I've seen plenty of
people with smashingly high V2s and that
will tell you almost nothing about their
HRV and the opposite. Okay. Now, the
research will show and I have seen this
personally in my experience. We've
coached a lot of men and a lot of women.
Women just tend to be a little bit lower
with their V2 max. Doesn't mean it's
worse, but it is just a little bit lower
of a score, meaning more sympathetic
drive, right? Not worse. Now that may
actually not mean that but that's a
conversation for another day. But
nonetheless little bit of calibration on
what this thing actually is. We now know
HRV influences and I won't say directly
and only causes something like attention
and focus has dozens if not hundreds of
things that regulate it. So we need to
make sure that we're hearing this
correctly. Right? It is just associated
with and it does influence but it's not
the only influence of everything from
attention to decision making emotional
control um and then other things like
what are called mental endurance now
this particularly matters because mental
endurance under stress is
resilience this is why we're talking
about it right I want you to be more
resilient to stress in this particular
example can you maintain decision-
making can Can you maintain focus? Can
you maintain attention and memory skills
in the presence of stress? Not just when
you're baseline, not when you're fresh
and okay, but what about when you become
fatigued? That's what a higher HRV
allows you to do. And that's why we're
going to press forward and give you
tools to improve it, enhance it, or if
it's already good, to maintain it. You
could drown yourself in data, whether
you want to look at systematic reviews
or meta analyses, but you'll find them.
Heart rate variability is associated
with an enormous number of health
implications. Everything from I'm I'm
being a little aggressive here, but
basically every psychological or mental
health metric, anxiety, depression,
PTSD, and so forth to things like
cardiovascular disease all cause
mortality, inflammation, hypoglycemia,
hyper lipidmia, hypertension. I mean,
pick your metric and you will find the
meta analysis or systematic review that
shows, man, a bad HRV is going to be
associated with bad health outcomes. One
example I can give you here is things
like that hypoglycemia. Now, that's
that's high blood sugar, right? So,
think type two
diabetes. Well, just think about it this
way. If you were in a state of fight or
flight, right? You were fighting for
your life. Your adrenaline would be up.
When your adrenaline goes up, your body
releases a bunch of glucose into the
bloodstream. And it does that because
glucose will then go to your skeletal
muscle. It gives him short-term energy
and it can prepare for combat in this
particular case. Doesn't actually matter
if you're fighting. General point is
this. Stress goes up, adrenaline goes
up, blood glucose goes up. Well, if this
is happening consistently throughout the
day, you're effectively giving yourself
stress induced diabetes because you're
constantly smashing your insulin system,
smashing the pancreas because you're
throwing blood glucose up and down and
you didn't do anything with food. This
is why high stress and chronic stress
management one of the many reasons at
least why these things are associated
with obesity they are associated with
inflammation there are associated with
high blood pressure and so forth there's
a direct physical reaction that happens
from your psychology in this case all
the way down to your molecular biology
and it has consequences across systems I
could keep giving you examples but I
think you get the point by now in fact
many of you may have already realized
are known that bad HRV is associated
with lots of bad health implications and
that's no good. What is less discussed
and less understood in my experience is
how it directly relates to resilience.
And there's a couple of interesting
papers that highlight this point and so
I want to dive into them in just a
little bit more detail now. But if you
remember your heart rate variability is
driven by your autonomic nervous system
and one of the main things within that
is called your vagus nerve. Now when we
hear Vegas, we often think down
reggulation, but it's not just that. If
you were to stimulate the Vegas nerve,
you could get arousal as well,
upregulation, excitement, so on and so
forth. It is this toggle, right? Is it
ability to go back and forth between
them. Well, we have evidence now
molecularly of how the vagus nerve can
directly activate and change the immune
system. No surprise here. What happens
when you are really cooked? You're shot,
overworked, overstressed. your immune
system gets compromised, right? Why?
Well, in part because of this. Now, I'm
not saying HRV caused that, but HRV
would provide you that signal. It says,
"Hey, this is why you're not as
resilient right now as you used to be.
Vegas nerve
overused, altered immune system
function, and now you got sick or got
more sick than you should have got
because of that overall stress response
you were less resilient to." Now,
another example of that is a really
complicated study, but it was so
beautiful. I wanted to point it out.
What they looked at here was this
resilience or what's called reactivity
marker. And so what they found is kind
of getting to the end of the paper here
was when you were in the state of low
HRV sympathetic drive that gave you
higher sleep reactivity to stress,
meaning when we exposed you to the same
stressor, you had a exaggerated sleep
response. In this case, a bad sleep
response. That's exactly what we're
talking about. So the same thing
happened to you when you had a higher
HRV didn't affect your sleep. Now when
we give that thing to you and you have a
low HRV it affects your sleep a lot.
That's higher reactivity that is being
less resilient to the same stressor. So
same stress bigger response. This is in
circular right because we also know at
the same point less sleep or worse sleep
increases your risk of all kinds of
problems. And in this specific paper,
the problem that they're looking at was
depression symptoms. So the lower amount
of sleep increased the risk of
experiencing higher depressive
symptoms. Many actually examples of
this, but that really does high again
encapsulates what I'm trying to talk
about here. It's not just up or down. It
is being more resilient to everything
that happens in your life. and our
autonomic nervous system is a great uh
tool to measure and pay attention to for
that. So, if that doesn't convince you,
I don't know what will, but I'm assuming
at this point you're all on board. So,
how do you actually measure it? Let's
talk about different ways where you can
actually investigate your HRV level.
Today's episode is sponsored by Element.
Element is an electrolyte drink mix that
has an ideal electrolyte ratio of
sodium, potassium, and magnesium, but no
sugar. Hydration is critical to
performance, both physical and mental
performance. Countless studies have
shown that even a slight degree of
dehydration, even as small as 1%, can
lead to decreases in physical output and
mental performance. We also know that
electrolytes are critical to proper
hydration, which I've been harping on
for years. But you can't do that proper
hydration by only drinking water. You
need to get the right amount of
electrolytes in the right ratios. And
that's why I'm a huge fan of Element. In
fact, many of you will probably remember
that I featured Element in my YouTube
series on optimizing hydration nearly 5
years ago. I featured Element in these
videos because their blend of 1,000 mg
of sodium, 200 milligs potassium, and 60
milligs of magnesium really is unique
and different than any other electrolyte
on the market. And it has great
scientific support. I use Element
constantly, particularly when I'm
sweating a lot, and I routinely make it
a part of my client's optimization
programs. If you'd like to try Element,
you can go to
drinklmnt.com/perform to claim a free
element sample pack with the purchase of
any Element drink mix. Again, that's
drinklmnt.com/perform to claim a free
sample pack. Today's episode is also
sponsored by Momentus. Momentus makes
the highest quality supplements on the
market, period. Many of you know me and
you know that I do not trust the vast
majority of supplement companies and for
good reason. Many studies have shown
that anywhere between 10 to up to 40% of
supplements have accidental
contaminants, intentional alterations,
mislabeling, or other serious issues.
But Momentus is different. I literally
spent years vetting the company, their
products, and leadership team before
personally officially partnering with
them in 2023. Every single one of
Momentus' products is third-party tested
to ensure quality, and many are even NSF
certified for sport. Now, while I love
all of their products, the ones I use
the most, both personally and with my
clients, are what I call the big three.
And these are the omega-3 fish oil,
creatine, and newly improved whey
protein formula. These three supplements
have fantastic data supporting their
benefits. Whey protein for lean muscle
mass, omega-3s for brain health, and
creatine for both muscle and brain
support. and they have been shown to be
very safe across basically all
populations of people, young, old, men,
women, etc. Now, nobody has to use
supplements, and I hope you never feel
pressured to do so. But if you're
interested in supplements, it's
important that you get them from the
highest quality providers. You don't
want mercury in your fish oil or lead in
your whey protein or anything like that.
So, that's why I stick exclusively to
Momentus. If you'd like to give Momentus
a try, go to live
momentous.com/perform to get 20% off
your order. Again, that's live
because HRV is so ubiquitous and you can
get it all from just your heart. There's
a ton of different cheap tools to
measure. I have used historically
something called Morpheus and it is
amazing for looking at changes in HRV
over time, especially at a baseline.
It's fantastic for improving your
conditioning and knowing what exercise
to do for the day. But the other ones I
want to get into today function a little
bit differently and that is kind of more
understanding an acute sense. What am I
at right now? And if I go do something,
can I see that change in instantly?
Oh, so for that actually I like a device
um that's a combination of a couple
things. Number one, I use a chest strap
Polar H10. I have no affiliation to
Polar. I buy it. It's about $100 or so.
Um this is the gold standard. And I like
this the most because it is actually
directly measuring uh EKG or ECG in the
heart. Others, the ones that are worn
like on your arm or on your wrist are
not directly measuring the heart.
They're using a a different technology
or methodology which doesn't matter.
then they're okay in some spaces. Some
of them are very good. But for me, if
I'm going to make a change, if I'm going
to pay attention, if I'm going to coach
somebody on it, I'm not going to try to
save 30 bucks and buying something
that's slightly cheaper. 100 bucks is
pretty reasonable for most people to get
to. And so I want the highest standard
there. So for me, I've just personally
had the most success with the Polar H10
strap. On top of that, I have recently
been shown by a colleague of mine, Dr.
Jay Wilds, W I L. Jay is phenomenal in
this area. He does a ton of of research
and clinical experience in this stuff.
He recently showed me an app called
Optimal HRV. Again, I have no
association to them. I pay normal full
price for it. It's about five bucks a
month. It's really, really cheap. It
pairs perfectly with that Polar H10
strap. So, you can put the strap on, you
can pull up the app, and you can see
your HIV in real time. So, we can see it
right now. we can go test something. We
can go try something and we can see the
response. It's very intuitive. So,
you're talking 115 bucks or something
like that. You could have yourself a
nice HRV tool. One more time to be
really clear, if we are concerned about
HRV, we're going to go with one of those
devices. We're going to measure it
directly from the chest. We're not going
to measure it from the finger or the
wrist or anywhere else unless we
absolutely have to. Now, it's been a
long time since we talked about this,
but earlier I brought up respiratory
rate, and I'm going to come back to it
now. There's not as much research here,
but it is growing. And what's clear
about respiratory rate is the
information you get from it is different
than what you get from heart rate
variability. And so, ideally, you're
going to pay attention to both of these.
Respiratory rate like HRV, it is a
non-specific but highly sensitive
measure of your nervous system. In other
words, if your HRV is up or down or your
respiratory rate is up or down,
something's happening. It's very
sensitive to changes. You will see
changes within a day. As I just
described, you can change these things
within minutes or seconds. If you see
changes over a couple of days, it means
something, but they're
non-specific. They're not telling you,
oh, this was your nutrition or, oh, this
is your mental stress or, oh, this is
hydration or bad sleep. You don't know
what's happening. It's simply telling
you something about the overallic load,
the total stress of the environment. So,
then you got to go work to figure out
what's happening there. But they are
both highly relevant. Why I like
respiratory rate the arguably the most
here is because I have personally and
now I'm walking away from the research
here. I can't show this scientifically
yet, but I have found it personally to
be more sensitive. It'll show up fast.
Oftentimes, not always, but oftentimes
in my personal experience, you'll see
changes in respiratory rate before
you'll see them in HRV. You know, in a
thing that matters, but not always. And
so we really pay high attention to both.
There's a really wonderful article in a
technology journal actually called
sensors uh published a couple years ago
u by a scientist that I just love in
this field Andre Nolo called the
importance of respiratory rate
monitoring from healthcare to sport and
exercise. And in that paper they walk
you through a ton of the research what's
going on here. um the fact that it is a
critical vital sign. It has been
associated with everything from cardiac
events and pneumonia um to heat exposure
and cold and exercise, emotional stress,
cognitive load and so on and so forth.
You can go read about more of the
details of respiratory rate there. I've
thrown this out a couple of times at the
beginning, but I wanted to finally tie a
bow on this as well. What does this have
to do with CO2 tolerance? If you're not
familiar with
that, this is a similar metric. So when
we're looking at respiratory rate and
we're looking at resting heart rate and
HRV, we also like to pay attention to
CO2 tolerance. This is a different way
of examining the state of your nervous
system. Specifically, the way that we
have defined CO2 tolerance, this is
developed, well rather was brought to me
by a gentleman named Brian McKenzie. I
don't know who created it initially, but
Brian is the one who taught me about it.
And the way that this works is it's
effectively like a little bit of a
breath hold test where you exhale
continuously and you can see how long
that you can continually exhale some
small amount of air. It's a maximum
effort test. In the show notes, we'll
put a direct link to a video Brian has
made that shows you how to go through
the CO2 tolerance test. And I like it.
We've used it a bunch. I also feel like
it tells us something similar but
slightly different than both HRV and
respiratory rate. So, while I told you
earlier we look at both of those, we
also look at CO2 as much as we can. I
can't get CO2 tolerance though from a
simple test on uh you know like a
resting test. You actually have to
actively do it. Only takes about a
minute. But because of that, people
won't necessarily do it every day where
I can check their heart rate easily
whether they're doing something or not.
So, that's the only reason why we don't
use it necessarily every day. But here's
the connection.
The way that your physiology works is
you will bring in oxygen when you take a
breath in. And you're doing that because
oxygen's primary job is to regulate
metabolism. It's energy production,
right? It's aerobic metabolism, which is
what most of your body is doing most of
the time. When you breathe out, you're
breathing out CO2. The difference
between oxygen and CO2 is that carbon
molecule. That carbon is a byproduct of
any metabolic process. So whether you're
breaking down carbohydrates or fat,
whether you're using that resulting
energy for exercise or digestion or
immune function or cognitive
performance, it doesn't actually matter.
It all is going to net result in you
leaving a little bit of water left over,
making some ATP, and having a bunch of
free floating carbon. That carbon in
your system is highly problematic. And
so your body will immediately attach it
to an oxygen molecule forming CO2. And
so the way we say this is the net end
result of all metabolic processes are
water, ATP and
CO2. Now if you're in the case of let's
just say exercise it doesn't matter but
let's just say we are doing that the
more metabolism you go through the more
CO2 is generated in your muscle. Your
muscle then puts it into your blood and
then transmits through your blood goes
into your lungs and then you exhale and
get it out. That's the entire cycle of
life. Plants do the opposite. They
breathe in CO2, pull out the carbon,
keep it, hold on it to themselves, and
then get rid of the O2. Right? That's
the the relationship living beings have
with plants in terms of oxygen and
CO2. Why this matters? Again, you
breathe in oxygen to regulate
metabolism, but your CO2 levels are
there to regulate your pH. It has
nothing to do with your exercise
performance. Your body will regulate
blood pressure. It will regulate
electrolytes and it will regulate pH
over almost anything. And one could
argue it will regulate pH literally over
anything else in the whole world. That
is because most of your body, the vast
majority of all enzymes in the world
have to run at a very specific pH. Too
acidic or too alkaline, they don't work.
If they don't work and your heart can't
pump and your brain can't operate, you
die pretty quickly. So, your
physiological pH levels are maintained
at an incredibly tight number. Your
testosterone can easily triple in a few
minutes. Your adrenaline can go up many
multiples. Your pH stays within an
extremely tight window. It will move
everything else around it to keep your
pH at the right level. The primary way
your body regulates your pH is by
changing the amount of CO2 that it lets
be in your blood. If CO2 levels get too
high in your blood, this will tell your
autonomic nervous system to breathe
more. You don't feel it. This is
subconscious. You're just breathing
more. You have no idea what's happening.
Not an active process. Autonomic nervous
system. It does that. It gets rid of the
CO2. It brings the acidic level down. If
the acidic level is too low, meaning
you're too alkaline, it will have you
slow your respiration down. You'll hold
your breath. Again, you won't even know
this. It'll let the CO2 levels increase
more until it gets to the spot it wants,
and then it'll bring your respiration
back up. If you go start exercising, you
start putting a bunch of CO2 in the
blood. That's why your body makes you
breathe
more because it has to dump that CO2.
In normal circumstances, the primary
reason you get air hunger or you feel
like you have to breathe, if I were to
hold make you hold your breath right
now, it's not because you're running low
on oxygen. It's because CO2 levels are
rising. CO2 concentrations in your blood
are the primary mechanism that drive you
to feel like you need to ventilate. So,
it can be conscious. You can feel it.
But most of the time, this is happening
without you having any awareness at all
of what's going on. If you are
chronically
breathing not enough, you are under
breathing, which doesn't happen
much, CO2 levels would be getting really
high, you'd be acidic. What's more
common is the
opposite. And there are papers on this,
right? That you can see it. If you are
breathing too much, whether you want to
call this over breathing like we tend to
call it, or if you are actually truly
into what's called chronic
hyperventilation, this is a medically
diagnosible condition. Chronic
hyperventilation is over breathing. What
that really is is you're putting too
much CO2 out of your body into the
atmosphere. So because of that, your CO2
levels in your body get too low. This is
called
hypocapnea. Too low of CO2. This is
incredibly problematic because again,
one, we are out of pH range now. We're
not acidic. We're alkaline. We're the
opposite. So, because of that, your
kidneys somewhere within a couple of
days or a couple of hours to a couple of
days, maybe even a few weeks, can
respond to that. They don't always, but
they can respond to that by putting you
into what's called metabolic acidosis.
And it's doing that because it's again
trying to reestablish some acidity in
the system to make everything happy.
This then has a whole host of renal and
kidney issues, hydration issues, and
sodium potassium and electrolyte issues
and a bunch of other stuff that is just
overall problematic. The other major
problem with this over breathing
strategy is CO2 is a vaso dilator. And
so if you are exhaling too much of it
and CO2 concentrations get too low, you
get vas constriction. This means
decreased cerebral blood flow. This
means decreased blood flow everywhere
else. It also alters what's called bores
effect. In general, what all this is
meaning, you don't have as much
oxygenation. Not exactly what it is, but
if that helps you conceptualize what's
going on here, then that's fine. And so,
we're seeing problems in health,
cognitive performance, physical exercise
performance, all of this stuff can be a
response to chronic hyperventilation or
over breathing, however you were define
those things. That said, then if I'm
seeing HRV is fine, resting heart rate's
fine, but I am chronically over
breathing, I still have some work to do.
And it is indicating something is
happening potentially from a stress
situation that's not going to be
necessarily picked up by changes in
sleep or changes in HRV or changes in in
overall resting heart rate. Why this
becomes really problematic is they can
then turn quickly into what are called
sustaining factors. And so while
something caused hyperventilation, which
is a normal and healthy response,
remember I say I get scared right now. I
want to go into sympathetic drive, I
want adrenaline up, I want to start an
anticipatory over breathing strategy. I
know CO2 is going to start increasing
because I'm about to start doing
something physically. So I'll start over
breathing. That's great. Normal reactive
strategy there, healthy one. That's what
we want. But if we're chronically doing
that, we're chronically over breathing
because we're chronically in this
sympathetic drive, we're chronically in
this high stress environment, that can
be sustained. It can turn into a habit.
It can turn into misattribution. It can
turn into lots of different things. We
have increased that sympathetic adinuric
tone. We are ready and dialed and primed
for the same situation, the same smell,
the same thing we hear, the same thing
we see to drive us back into that
hyperventilation strategy.
we then can be causing the same problem
and it can be cyclical right because
that hyperventilation itself can cause
the same physiological problems. So it's
hard strategy to break. So really
important to pay attention to
respiratory rate as well. I could go on
but again for the sake of time we'll
stop right there. Important highly
correlated highly overlapped with some
of the other markers we've talked about
but it tells us unique information.
Now, how do I measure this? Most of the
wearables you have will measure
respiratory rate. I will give you fair
warning. There is no industry standard
though on how that's calculated. So,
just like HRV, don't put a ton of stock
in the absolute number. You want to pay
most attention to trends and things like
that, but at least be consistent with
the device that you're using. Use
whatever you like. It doesn't matter
what you get, how you use it. It's a
very simple measure that basically every
variable either directly has or it can
have. If they're not reporting it,
they're measuring it. They're just using
it to calculate other stuff. So, um,
that can be done in a bunch of different
ways. Hopefully, that gave you some more
information about how you can calculate
HRV, how you can calculate respiratory
rate. You probably can infer how to
calculate resting heart rate. And I gave
you some tools on how to calculate and
measure CO2 tolerance as well. It's time
for us to now move on to where we find
figure out how to make sense of all that
information and determine how do we
interpret it all. We're going to start
off by talking about HRV. Anyone who
works in this area will be squeamish
when you ask them the question of what's
a good one or bad one. We all say the
same thing, which actually to me is like
a badge of honor that that person knows
what they're talking about when I hear
them say that. It's a hard thing to put
a number on. I'll give you something
though to get started. On most
wearables, most men are going to be
something in the like 40s to 60 range on
their HRV score. Women are a little bit
lower than that. If you are older than
say 60 years old, then maybe tink that
down a little
bit. That all said, I I wanted to start
out with a number, but I don't know what
that even means. And that's because
every device actually has a different
calculation they use to measure HRV. So
we're not even necessarily always
talking about the same thing. More
importantly than that though, there is a
misuse of HRV in a bunch of different
scenarios. So you should pay attention
to it. I made a long argument of why
it's important. It's relevant. But I
just started off by also saying the the
measurement itself is not the same
between devices. So, we want to use this
as a measure of progress or or
regression rather than just comparing
score to score. Especially if you're
comparing your score to your friends and
you're on a ring and they're on a watch
or something like that. The the numbers
actually the the calculation the
equation itself can be completely
different. There's many many ways to
calculate HRV that are scientifically
validated and the numbers are digits
different than the other ones. So,
that's an important point to pay
attention to. I've already also talked
about the fact that it could be normal
for you when you have an HRV score that
is let's just to put numbers on it say
25. Well, that actually might be normal
for you. I don't know. If we look at
your respiratory rate and your resting
heart rate and your CO2 tolerance and
your subjective feeling and your
recovery and your performance and your
cognition and they're all great, well
then I might not be super worried about
just your HRV. So we're never going to
take it of itself by itself and only
itself and over interterpret its
meaning. If you are going to calculate
it, please collect good data. What do I
mean by that? However you're testing it,
be consistent. If you're wearing a ring,
wear a ring. Use the same one. If you're
testing it with a chest strap every
morning, use it in the same position.
Don't take it seated one day. Don't take
it lying down the next day. Don't wake
up and go to the bathroom one day and
then check it and the next day you did
it before going to the bathroom or you
did it before breakfast and then you had
coffee the next time and you had a giant
pancake breakfast. You get the point
here. Test it under the same consistent
terms always. We want to pay attention
mostly to trends over time. And the
recommendation I'll give you here is to
establish your own standard deviation.
Here's what that means. Let's say you
test your HRV for 30 days and within
those 30 days, don't do anything about
it. Don't make any changes. On a piece
of paper, in an Excel file on your
computer, just jot down all the score on
all 30 of those days. Then ask it to run
a standard deviation calculation. And
this will basically tell you what your
normal average number is and how far off
up or low you tend to go within a 30-day
window. This matters a ton because the
amount of that deviation number one
tells us something about your physiology
that's maybe arguably more important
than the actual number itself. Let me
give you some mathematical examples.
Let's say your HRV was 30 on your
device. Whatever 30 is, whatever that
means, it doesn't matter. And you
calculated it after a month and it said
your average is 30 and your standard
deviation was 20. That means you swing
all the way down to 10 all the way up to
50. That is a very large standard
deviation. Other people your standard
deviation might be three or five. And so
you have to know what matters to you. If
your standard deviation is 20 and you
wake up one day and instead of being at
30, which is your average, you're at 27,
that means nothing to you. That is
nothing because that's a that's so such
a low percentage of your normal
deviation. The opposite person whose
standard deviation is normally five and
they wake up and they're seven high or
low, then that actually tells them
something's going on that that their
system is responding to. So if you want
my honest answer of how to use HRV the
most appropriate, this is what we're
paying attention to. Typically, again,
just a rule of thumb here, people that
are more stable in their HRV are
generally better. If you have a score
that is doubling every other day, we
would immediately start thinking, "All
right, this person's hyperreactive.
Whatever they're doing is causing a huge
change in their autonomic nervous
system. We need to create more stability
here." That's how we become more
resilient. That's how we become more
predictable. That's what we're after. If
you're so tight, no matter what you do,
we're getting the same response every
day. Then we know that system is
actually quite stable. And no matter
what insult hits you that day, work
stress, environmental toxin, who cares?
Your body is able to handle it. You're
not hitting the wall on the highway.
You're go you're you're moving left and
right, right? Your car is swerving, but
you're not hitting the wall. So those
numbers aren't changing. That's where
we're bringing back that highway
analogy. And that's what we're talking
about when we're talking about nervous
system stability. So we never make
changes based on one day. We never use a
cheap consumer wearable to tell us how
to live our life. To exercise today or
to not exercise, to sleep today or to
not sleep today. That is, and I think
the people behind uh most of these
companies would say the same thing.
That's not the best way to use something
like an HRV score. Interpret your
numbers in the appropriate context. But
regardless, we should be able to get
better and become more resilient in our
overall nervous system responses to
stress. back to our highway analogy.
What causes people to be more stable
versus less stable with their HRV is a
bunch of different stuff, genetics, but
and then it's also the dumb stuff. U it
is in a regular sleep schedule. Once we
get people sleeping just in a consistent
time, HRV almost always goes up. It in
fact so much so it is very often the
first thing I look at when somebody asks
me about their HRV or we're going
through their overall analysis of all
their data and we see HRV is poor. My
eyes go right up to sleep regularity. If
their sleep is irregular, then I
honestly don't go much past that. When
their sleep regularly goes up, HR just
goes up. So, if you're like, man, I've
been doing everything. I've been doing
blah blah blah blah. My HV doesn't go up
and your sleep's irregular. Well, that's
stop number one on the train. Other
stuff is honestly, sorry to be sound
this way, but it's kind of what I call
the dumb stuff. It's alcohol. It is uh
lots of bad negative health habits. All
this stuff will bring it down. So, if
you remove all those from the equation,
it's probably going to go up. Another
one I wanted to bring up here um that
people don't pay a lot of attention to.
Two things have stood out when I was
diving back through some of our
databases. One was wild changes in
exercise within the same week. So what I
mean by that is if you're pretty
standard throughout the week and then
you're the type of person who goes
bonkers with your exercise in the
weekend, we see this huge instability of
HRV. So whether you, you know, you do
your 10 mile run in the weekend or you
do the multiple classes or you like to
play five hours of pickle ball or
whatever and it is drastically different
than your week, that will also explain a
lot of instability with your HRV and
your resting heart rate for that matter.
So that one will sneak up on people. And
the last one I'll bring up is actually
nutrition related feeding frequency of
food. Specifically, we have had a number
of people come in for sleep related
issues, whether that is really bad sleep
or just kind of sub-optimal sleep, and
they're eating one meal a day. Now, I'm
not fundamentally opposed to one meal a
day, but in our experience, this has led
to really, really compromised HRVs. What
has happened many times is these
individuals feel good, okay, or great
for 30 days or 45 days, maybe up to 90
days, but then you see the the nervous
system just starting to pay the price.
I'm not trying to indicate that one meal
a day is bad for your health. Again, I'm
going on my personal experience and the
data we have in our companies and and
we've just seen it not go well. And
we've at the same time seen people then
who eat more frequently in terms of they
were eating one meal a day and they
change and go to two or three and the
nervous system sends to recover. Want to
be real clear here. I don't only mean
their HRV score that does happen. But
it's other signs and symptoms as well.
It's objective measures of say sleep
quality um cognitive function,
performance and so forth. They feel
good, but their physiology in the longer
term isn't uh responding how they they
think or hoping it really is. So, if you
are a one meal a day, fine, great. If
you feel awesome, awesome. Keep doing
it. I'm only bringing this up to where
if you've made a change recently and
you're like, "What the heck? Why why is
my HB going down?" that I think is the
most appropriate way to to interpret it
as this is maybe one of the things that
happens with um lack of feeding
throughout the day is it creates some
potentially somewhat of a of a
neurological or nervous system stressor
that will alter HRV. So, lots of other
things I could bring up here, but those
are the ones that I thought were most
interesting. It's a combination of some
of the stuff that is most well
documented, the alcohol, the emotional
regularity, so on and so forth, with
some things I thought that maybe some of
you would find interested in that we've
just seen behind the scenes that is not
necessarily in the peer-reviewed
literature. Today's episode is sponsored
by EightLe. Eightlee makes smart
mattress covers with cooling, heating,
sleep tracking, and more. I've
personally been sleeping on an eightle
mattress cover for years now, and it's
absolutely glorious. I love it so much
that I hate traveling away from home
because it means I can't sleep on my
eightle Pod 4 Ultra. As you'll hear me
talk about endlessly on this podcast,
there really is nothing you can do that
makes more of an impact on your health
and performance than getting tremendous
sleep. And getting great sleep requires
having your body temperature drop a
couple of degrees at night. And that's
hard to do on your own. The eight sleep
has been a game changer for me because I
run hot at night or as my wife calls it,
I'm a furnace. If I don't have something
like an eight sleep helping me cool
down, I'll wake up in the middle of the
night overheating and not feeling great.
This is something I've also found in
many of the people that I coach,
especially those who are really
physically active. The EightLe Pod 4
Ultra has two times more cooling power
yet is virtually silent and it has
highfidelity sleep tracking and even has
snoring detection that'll automatically
lift your head a few degrees to improve
air flow and stop your snoring. If you'd
like to try eight, go to
eight.com/perform to save $350 off your
Pod 4 Ultra. Eightlee currently ships to
the US, Canada, the UK, select countries
in the EU and even Australia. Again,
that's
eight.com/perform. We have a little bit
of an algorithm we use when determining
if a change in HRV matters to us. So,
how do you interpret this context?
Number one, we always check to make sure
we got good data. I talked about that
earlier. If they don't, then I disregard
it. But let's say they do. Most of the
time they do. So, we've got good data,
however you define that. The next
question I'm asking is, are we talking
about one day or is this been happening
for more than three, ideally more than
five to seven days? If it is acute,
single day, second day, third day only,
then I'm asking the next set of
questions, which is okay, what are we
doing with your training right now? If
we're in a phase where we're trying to
cause physiological adaptations, I'm
trying to stress you. So, if your HRV is
lower and I'm seeing signs of stress,
that's exactly what we're pushing for.
That's a good thing. We're not changing
anything. This is one of the huge flaws
of general technologies that just tell
you what to do with your workout, your
nutrition based on today's score. Oh,
your HRV is low, therefore take a day
off. That's a really bad approach
because it doesn't understand what
you're trying to do in the long term or
even the medium-term in this case. So,
if we see an HIV that is low and it's
been down for two or three days and
we're in a phase, we're in the
offseason, we're trying to build up
change, we're in a caloric deficit and
we're working hard, we're try, I don't
care. You are a little bit stressed,
that's the point. That's going to cause
adaptation. we're going to ignore. That
said, if we're in a phase where we're
supposed to be peing, I'm trying to feel
good, whether we're peing for sports
performance or you're simply saying, I
need to be on today. I need to have a
great day. This is a really important
thing I'm doing in my family life or
work life or something like that. My
HV's been down for a couple of days and
I got to get it fixed because I'm trying
to perform at my best right now. Then
we're going to do what I call acute
state shifters. And I got a whole
category of these things to cover for
you here in one second. But I'm going to
give them tons of different strategies
that they can pull out one or more of
these acute shifters. And I promise you
these will make that HRV go up right
now. They'll go up today. They'll
probably be up again tomorrow. And
you'll be fine. You'll be back in the
sweet spot. Going back up our algorithm
a little bit. If we got good data and
this has not just been a one or two day
thing, but it's been here for five or
seven or 10 days or longer, then I'm
gonna ask the same follow-up question.
Number one, are we trying to induce
adaptation? If
so, I'm not going to ignore it, but I'm
going to watch it carefully. Not
necessarily going to change your workout
program today, but we are going to watch
it carefully. If it is really
suppressed, meaning it's more than two
standard deviations outside your normal
for more than five days, we're going to
take action. We're going to do
something. Okay? If that was really
technical for you, if it's a really big
change and it's been around a long time
and you're really feeling bad, your
motivation, your energy, you feel junky,
then then we're going to we're going to
take action. Okay?
If we're in a phase where we're trying
to perform our
best and that's been down for a long
time, then we're going to go to what I
call chronic solutions. So, we have our
acute solutions and our chronic
solutions. And so, ultimately, we want
to make sure we're using the right tool
for the right task. Now, I'm going to go
through all those briefly, but before we
do that, I want to finish talking about
respiratory rate as well, because it's a
little bit of a different
interpretation. I've given you some
sample numbers earlier. I kept saying 14
breaths per minute or 15 breaths per
minute and I'm doing that because the
literature will show you the cutoff line
seems to be about 16 breaths per minute.
If you are over 16, there is clear and
consistent literature tying that to
everything from risk of a cardiovascular
event, myioardial inffection or stroke
or things like that is tied to clinical
deterioration, pain, uh emotional
stress, cognitive load, and a whole host
of things that you don't want to be
anywhere near. If you are at 16, you're
right on that line. Yeah, I'm not trying
to overly scare you, but if you're above
that, I'm going to make the case that
you, as long as our data are accurate,
which is again a whole another question,
but if you are up there, then we have a
case of chronic over breathing. Whether
that is chronic hyperventilation, that's
a medical diagnosis, not for me to
decide, but you are over breathing in my
opinion. And we're going to want to
bring that thing down. Most of the time
I'm looking at if you are in the 10 to
14 range and then I don't see anything
else. I'm good here. If you're 15, I'm
asking a lot of follow-up questions.
You're 15 16 I'm probably going to ask
us to do something. If we have bunch of
other major issues, maybe I'm not too
worried about it. But if you're over 16,
then this is going to be one of our top
tier priorities. All right? Because of
all the reasons I shared earlier about
what happens when you're over
ventilating.
lots of short and long-term issues. And
so this is exactly how we interpret
those numbers. Let's say you're at 16 or
17. Okay, very first stop on this train.
I want to make sure your breathing
mechanics are okay. Very simple first
principles here. If you are ineffective
with your breathing strategy, whether
you're you're breathing through your
shoulders and your neck, clicular
breathing, whether your diaphragm
doesn't work appropriately, your
intercostals are weak, your position or
your posture is bad so bad that it's
infecting your breathing. Well, then you
can't breathe well, you're going to have
to bring more often. This is simply if
you're weak in a spot, you have to do it
more often. If you you can imagine being
hunched over, right? Touch your front of
your shoulder to your knee and try to
breathe. You can't. So, you're going to
breathe more frequently to get the same
amount of air in. That's an exaggerated
example, but you get the point. So,
number one, before I'm worried about
some long-term intervention with you, I
just want to make sure that it's not a
mechanical
issue. Past
that, we're going to look at breathing
problems. And what I mean by that are
everything from allergies to nasal
blockage to clinical sleep disorders. If
you can't breathe through your nose,
there's a strong chance you're going to
be hyperventilating. It's not a
guarantee, but we've just seen that
really highly associated. So, step
number one, the way that we're going to
interpret this higher respiratory rate.
Okay, maybe it's a sign that mechanical
breathing technique is not great. Nope.
How's your nose? Oh, yeah. I'm stuffed
up all the time. Hm. Have polyps? Can
you breathe through your nose ever? No,
never. Are you mouth breather? Okay,
great. Then we're going right there. I'm
not going into anything else past this
until we fix breathing out of your nose.
Dehydration can do the same thing. So if
you just notice your respirator rates up
one particular day, oh my gosh, and then
you properly hydrate, it probably goes
back down. Nothing to worry about long
term there. After that, things get a
little bit more work intensive. So it
could be a CO2 intolerance thing. If
you're highly sensitive to that CO2,
your brain can sometimes get
miscalibrated. It thinks there's way too
much CO2 in the system than there
actually is. So you're either hyper
stressed or or hyper sensitive and so it
starts asking you to dump and offload
that CO2 way sooner than it needs to.
You're intolerant or hyper sensitive,
one of those two. In that case, we can
confirm that. So we see your respiratory
rate is elevated. We also then run that
CO2 tolerance test on you. Oh, that's
also poor. Then great, we don't need to
do anything else with your respiratory
rate. We fixed your CO2 tolerance and
that respiratory rate will take care of
itself. Other things to think about
here, if your rest rate is high, it
could just be a long-term pattern.
Remember earlier when I talked about how
these can go from initiating factors to
sustaining factors. If you and we've
experienced this a lot in our middle um
to later aged uh adults, right? These
are often folks that came from high
stress
environments, high stress careers,
whether these have been lots of former
surgeons, u military individuals, um
entrepreneurs, things like that, or they
just had high stress for a long period
of time. The over breathing was
appropriate because they were in a
stressful environment. And then they
sell the company, they retire, they
reduce their hours, and then years later
they're still over breathing. And in the
cases where we've had years of data on
people, we've seen this uh confirmed
pretty well. That pattern just exists.
You're just over breathing and you don't
know it. So that has happened a lot. You
got to go break that pattern. One of the
biggest causes of this has actually been
pregnancy. A lot of things can happen
post having a child for women. And those
patterns can be established and stay
permanent unless you go back in there
and actively reframe and rebuild the new
pattern. Last one. Then here is what we
would finally call general elevated
alatic load. whether this is physical or
mental. Remember alistatic load is that
colloquial term for kind of like global
stress on your body no matter how it
comes in or not. I went through all that
list for a bunch of reasons, but one of
them is I want you to to realize that
that stress thing is at the the last
one. We don't look at respiratory rate
and go, "Oh, you're stressed." That's
that could be, but it could simply be
the fact you can't breathe out of your
nose. It could be something you're not
hydrated. It could be the fact that
you're just intolerant or sensitive to
CO2 or any number of reasons. And that
is the pecking order. That's the
strategy we go off of when we try to
solve those simple problems first. And
in our experience, you get through one
through four mechanics, breathing
problems, hydration, and CO2 tolerance.
Most of the time, your situation is
solved. Whether you pick any of the
metrics I just talked about today, heart
rate or respiratory rate or anything
else or you pick something else entirely
different. I think most of us in this
field would agree you should not be
overly fixated on one metric. There is
no best number here. And there's
problems with data and interpretation
and normative values and so forth.
Things like stress, things like recovery
are multiaceted. You need multiple
objective and subjective measures before
you get too excited. Let's actually
finally talk about what some of these
interventions are and how we can improve
overall nervous system resilience. It
makes sense for us to start off with the
acute changes. This is the stuff you can
do right now in any given moment and it
will change how you're feeling and
experiencing life. It will shift your
state. You already know this. This is
what I call the 4x4 matrix. So picture
on one part of the matrix your
physiology on another part your
autonomic nervous system. What I'm going
to share with you is how physiology can
change autonomic nervous system and it
can make it go up or it can make it go
down. Autonomic nervous system can do
the same thing with physiology. So, it's
a four-way street here. Really easy
examples. If you want to make your
physiology change your autonomic nervous
system and you want to make it go up,
just scream. Yell right now. Flex your
muscles as hard as you possibly can. You
do anything like that with your physical
body, that will cause your autonomic
nervous system to change
instantaneously. Heart rate will go up,
respiratory rate will change, adrenaline
levels. You pick your metric physiology
directly increasing autonomic nervous
system activity. You can also do the
opposite. You could do a physiological
double sign. You could do progressive
muscle relaxation. You simply relax your
forearm and this could cause a change in
your autonomic nervous system. You get
the idea. That is physiology to ANS. ANS
to physiology is basically the opposite.
You get scared. Big shot of adrenaline
happens. This will physically increase
your strength capacity, force
production, and power output in your
muscles. An autonomic nervous system
change. You could do this with a
supplement or a drug. We could go down.
You could be more zen. You could take
again a medication. It could lower your
heart rate. And because of that, it
could have a physical response as well.
So, you intuitively know the answer. you
want to change and regulate your
autonomic nervous system, you have the
capacity and you already know the basics
of it. I break these acute and chronic
actions up into a bunch of different
categories. For me that looks like there
are food based solutions, there are
supplements, there are thermal
stressors, so temperature, of course
there's breath work, there are what I
call brain distractions or brain
alterations, basic rest or sleep,
there's light things you can do like
physical light. There's movement stuff,
physical movement, and then there's what
I call motivation. Tons and tons and
tons of examples. Most of them though
are acute. Let's take motivation for
example. If you scrolled on social media
and came across a a phenomenal uh
Cameron Haynes or Jo Willink quote, you
might get inspired. That could change
your autonomic nervous system. That
could change your arousal state. Right
now, you might have been low energy,
lethargic. That could put you in more
sympathetic drive. Your your HRV will
change if it is actually sufficiently
motivating to you. You could read a
story or a book or watch a movie. You
could do a physical warm-up, start
training, do some hops. I mentioned
earlier, flex as hard as you can. if I
shine a bright light directly in your
face. All these things would change your
state in the moment, but none of those
are going to make your chronic HRV
improve over time. These are mostly
short-term solutions. The chronic ones
are a little bit more difficult. Okay,
this is when we get into stuff like BOF
feedback training. If you have sleep
issues, getting a chronic sleep
improvement. If you are chronically
underex
exercised, start exercising more. um if
you are really off particularly if you
are low in caloric intake you're
hypocchloric for too long this might
have a chronic effect of of bringing
more calories back and then there are
things like again thermal exposure that
can have a chronic effect but most of
that stuff is pretty direct and acute
give you really easy example I've been
doing a cold water immersion cold water
exposures for a very long time I do not
use them because I think it adds a
minute to my life I do not use them to
burn more fat. You guys can all debate
whether or not you think those things
exist, but for me, we have used it for
stuff like this. We actually ran a bunch
of experiments. Uh we never published
this stuff. We didn't take it through
IRB. We just ran it with a bunch of our
athletes. And what we found was if you
looked at somebody's HRV very
specifically, then you put them in a a
cold bath, cold water for 2 to 5
minutes, how cold? I don't know. Um in
American units here, somewhere between
30 to 50°. It didn't really matter that
much to be honest. And you sat them
there. Here's what would happen. Your
HRV immediately post the ice bath when
you got out would go down. No surprise.
If you get in cold, really cold water,
you get sh shot immediately into
sympathetic drive. Low HRV. Remember,
fight or flight.
However, as quickly as 30 minutes
post, your HRV will be 10 to 20%
higher, more downregulated than you were
before the cold. And that continued to
increase for about the next 3 hours or
so. And we ran this stuff by actually
checking HRV like every 15 minutes for
several hours. So, we had 30 minutes
post, 45 minutes post, 60 minutes post,
etc., etc., all the way up to 180 post.
And we stopped measuring that then. and
still 180 minutes post cold water
immersion HRV was higher significantly
higher 25 to 50% depending on the person
higher three hours after the cold bath
and so while I know that most of us
think about it as like that short-term
thing no I don't have peer-reviewed
publications on this but we saw this
enough to where I was like yeah okay
great and it also stacked up with what I
feel it's going to last day now will
this last weeks and months I don't know
so probably if I had to guess but it
certainly will give you a nice acute
bump. And by acute, I mean several hours
and several days, right? If you hate the
ice, you think it is terrible or you
don't like it at all, fine. I got a 50
more examples I can give you. It's just
one that that showed up as really clear
evidence to us. Changing gears
entirely, you can do this without moving
your physical body at all, without
suffering, by just doing what are called
visual resets. Mentioned him a couple of
times now, but thank you, Dr. Andrew
Huberman. some of his early podcasts on
his uh his platform, his show talked a
lot about this, but visual resets, I
know his lab worked on it a lot, are
really compelling and really effective.
Lots of ways you can do this. There are
simple drills like eye circles. So, you
just stand there and basically run a big
loop with your eyes circling around.
That will change your sympathetic drive.
Other ones that again my colleague Emily
High Totower I know uses a lot are
things like a smooth H. You can see this
and the literature is really clear here.
There's lots of different cortical and
and visual resets, but this stuff is
really fantastic and super effective. A
different one entirely that I think a
lot of you exercisers and strength
trainers will like. It's a modified
Volva maneuver. the Volvo maneuver and
is that intraabdominal pressure that you
create when you're doing things like
lifting weights or having a bowel
movement. This is exactly how you use
it. Again, we're still talking about
chronic or acute rather. This is
something you're going to do right now.
It's not going to fix your long-term
stuff, but it'll give you that change
when you're feeling like you need it
right now. So, you're going to hold your
breath. You can do an inhale and hold,
or you can do an exhale and hold. It
doesn't really matter, but you're going
to hold and then create a bunch of
intraabdominal pressure. And what's
really key about this is the pressure
needs to be in a true
360°ree range. Here's the analogy I like
on this one. Imagine you are a can of
soda. So, you're a barrel, if you will.
And the bottom of the barrel that's
sitting flat on the ground is your
pelvic floor. And the top is your
diaphragm. So, these are running
parallel to each other. And then the
barrel or the can of soda, however you
like to think about it, is everything
from the front of your stomach to the
side of your stomach all the way to your
back. You want to create pressure
against all of those surfaces. So
imagine you're trying to explode that
barrel every way. You're trying to blow
the bottom out. So blow the bottom into
the ground. You're trying to blow the
top up in the air. And you're trying to
blow every side out each individual way.
Right? That's how we do. It's not just a
crunch. It's not a back extension. It's
not anything else. It is a all quadrants
vertical and horizontal. And you're
going to do that and you're going to
hold it for 10
seconds. In doing that, you're going to
see your heart rate jump from, you know,
60 70 beats per minute to 120. It'll
shoot way way way up in the air. But
then at the end of those 10 seconds, you
exhale. And actually, that the
literature suggests that it doesn't
really matter how you exhale. Go slowly.
Go through your mouth. Go through your
nose. kind of let it all dump out
quickly. It doesn't actually matter that
much. In doing that, that heart rate
will go from 110 or 120 all the way now
down to like 40 or 50. So, before you
started the drill, you were at 60 or 70
and now your new baseline is
significantly lower. Really effective.
You can do it anywhere. It takes just a
few seconds to do. Doesn't cost you any
money at all. And it is particularly
good at altering what are called
barrower receptors that have specific
action on that vagus nerve. And so you
can do this. The magnitude of effect is
actually really really
high. You'll hear in a second, but
there's different technology you can use
to directly stimulate your vagus nerve,
but the magnitude of effect is much
lower than something like this Volva. So
it's free, it's cheap, it's easy, you
can do it a bunch, and it has a big uh
magnitude of effect.
Couple of caveats here with this
modified balsa though. If you are prone
to orthostatic issues, you pass out a
lot. You have low blood pressure. Don't
do this. Don't do this if you're by
water or in a pool or in the ocean. Uh
don't do this a whole bunch of times.
Probably don't do this immediately
during your
workout. All the caveats aside, right?
You're going to create a bunch of
intraabdominal pressure. You're going to
block a lot of blood flow, if not oluded
entirely. Don't pass out. Don't fall
into water. Don't drown. Don't do all
that stuff. Another option, like I just
mentioned, are what are called those
veagal nerve stimulators. These are
somewhat new. There are a handful of FDA
approved devices that you can use. You
generally have to have a prescription to
get them, though. You can buy a ton of
these as normal consumers, and I have
not been impressed with any of them. The
data are, I would say, weak at best on
them. I have personally used many of
them and found like I got nothing out of
it. The people we had try it got nothing
out of it at all. The studies that are
the most
supportive are ones that are funded by
the companies themselves. So that
doesn't inherently mean the data are
wrong or bad or manipulated, but you all
know what that means. So for me, when it
comes to these these commercially
available nerve
stimulators, until we can see some more
independent testing done and the and the
data are more impressive, uh I generally
don't like to use them. That said, if
you've had a different experience and
you like it a lot, that's by all means
that's great. Use it. I have tried some
of the clinical ones, the FDA approved
ones, the ones that require a
prescription, and those are far more
powerful. Those have been effective. I
specifically have used one called the
Gamma Core. You have to have a RX for
it, as I mentioned. Uh, no affiliation
to the company, but it is quite
effective. You you'll notice it pretty
substantially. your data will change
almost instantaneously if you're if
you're measuring it and monitoring it.
Mostly when it comes to these things,
these are coming from
neurologists, people with severe
migraines. This is just generally the
application. This is not something of
that we often think about if somebody's
like trying to make their HIV score
better today. So don't swing a
sledgehammer at a at a fly, if you know
what I mean. But these things are out
there. Hopefully that gives you a sense
of a bunch of different tools and
strategies. I intentionally picked
things all over the map. Cold water to a
breathing drill uh to technology from
free to a little bit more expensive and
a whole bunch of other things in between
that can shift or improve that state
instantaneously. We're going to
transition now and finish up by talking
about some of the things that will
actually make improvements chronically.
So, let's get you out of that hole and
let's make you a more permanent, more
resilient nervous system. Remember our
goal. We want to desensitize. We want
that system running in the background
and for us to have the ability to have
some control over it when we
want. If you think about basic
desensitization, the exact same
principles apply here. Which means you
can already intuitit a lot of the
solutions. I'll give you some again what
the science shows us, what we've
experienced, but there's obviously many
many more things or an unending list of
stuff you could try. Think about this
from the perspective of the immune
system. Now, I'll tell you a personal
story. My daughter has an incredibly
severe allergy to cashews. We put her
through a treatment. It took us about 18
months and she now eats cashews every
day. Right? We were in a position for
when she was younger to have to carry an
EpiPen with us. If there was cashew dust
in the air, you know, there's a non-zero
chance that she could die. It was that
severe. How did that program work?
basic
desensitization. You give them a very,
very, very small
load. Don't put anything else in the
system that could irritate them. As time
goes on, you give them a slightly higher
amount of load until she got up to
eating again multiple cashews a day. If
you look at a totally different system,
another personal experience I had many
years ago, I had an athlete who was
struggling a lot with low back pain. I
called a colleague of mine, a physical
therapist, Dr. Quinn Heno. Quinn was
fantastic and he basically said, "Hey,
you're dealing with low back pain. Take
her all the way up to the point of low
back pain. Go right below that line and
then train a bunch. Don't hurt her.
Don't exaggerate it." Right? Don't give
my daughter a bunch of cashews and cause
a huge reaction. That makes the system
worse, more sensitive, right? It's on
high alert. No, no, no. Small doses and
then and build those doses up and
desensitize the back pain. Worked
perfectly well. the athlete has it's
been years that athletes not had back
pain, chronic low back pain ever
since. Completely different. And again,
I'm showing you wildly different
examples here because I want you to
understand, in my opinion, this is a
ubiquitous physiological thing. This is
not specific to HRV, specific to the
nervous system. It seems to be just a
renowned physiological principle. So, it
carries a ton of weight. This looks a
lot of different ways. I'm just going to
give you some samples.
The research is going to show you most
of the time practices in this area,
you're going to start to see changes in
three to four weeks. You should feel
noticeable changes, but it won't be a
week. It won't be a day. 3 to four weeks
seems to be the number. The biggest
impact seems to come around the 6 to 8
week mark. Consistently dosing for that
long. Past 8 weeks, you don't see as
much continued progress. And so what
often times happens is you can whatever
you're doing, you can kind of back it
down from doing it once or twice every
day to maybe two or three times a week.
So you're kind of at a maintenance
dosage from there. That's what my
daughter is with her cashews. She has a
little bit of cashews a couple times a
week and that keeps her immune system
totally at bay. As we as far as we
understand it, if we were to do that,
pull the cashews away for a couple of
months, she might actually regress all
the way back to the beginning.
Okay, again, some analogy that helps
help there. If you were to think about
this from a growing muscle
perspective, nobody in their right mind
would go do one workout and then go to
bed that night and go, "Ah, my biceps
aren't any bigger. This stuff sucks. It
doesn't work. Strength training is a
joke. It's fake." Woke up the next day,
my arms aren't any bigger. Like, you
just you just know that doesn't work,
right? But yet, we expect the same thing
to happen when we do breath work. Uhhuh.
I've been doing it for two days. Nothing
happened. My HRV score is the same.
Sure. Of course it is. This is a system
approach. This is a desensitization.
You're reframing. You're building a new
road here. It's going to take several
weeks. That's where the benefit comes.
If you feel better right now when you do
it, great. That was an acute thing. But
we're trying to get to chronic changes,
right? So, we want to be active now so
that it can be passive later. What that
means is during these first four to
eight
weeks, it's work. It's a lot. You're
going to have to dedicate 10 to 15
minutes a day of doing something that
you're not going to necessarily feel
that much better in doing. But if you do
this appropriately, we reset this
baseline, then you could be on to
maintenance dosage and not have to
actively do this so much. So, there's a
bunch of examples for you. I'm going to
go through a handful right now. And
again, I've intentionally tried to
choose these from a wide variety of
activities. So, let's dive into them.
Very first one we're going to start with
is exercise. You know about the hormetic
stressor effects of exercise, right? You
break it down to build it up. Not
exactly what happens, but that's what
hormesis is, right? Small insult, come
back better. We saw this with cold. You
get really, really cold, you dive into
sympathetic drive, which then has this
compensatory response into
parasympathetic. Same thing here. Same
thing else. You can look across the
research. I've got some papers
specifically I pulled up that'll be in
the show notes. Strength training, low
intensity cardiovascular training,
highintensity intervals, all of it
works. If you want to directly compare
them, looks like highintensity interval
training seems to be the best for this
specific
marker. Same time, if you're doing max
effort high intensity intervals every
single day, you're going to run into a
hole. you're gonna run into a wall and
it's going to go down eventually. So,
dose appropriately. We use a little bit
of all of it. If we feel like somebody's
doing way too much highintensity work,
we will pull it back and HRV will
improve. Respiratory rate will come
down. Resting heart rate will come down.
I've seen that more times than I can
count. That said, if you're not
exercising at all or you're exercising a
little bit or moderate amount or you
don't go that high of intensity very
often, we will see the same positive
responses by adding highintensity
training. Whether that's higher
intensity strength training, higher
intensity interval training or
cardiovascular training, same thing. So,
this is just about the right dose for
the right overall experience. Totally
dependent upon your lifestyle and sleep
and nutrition and blah blah blah blah
blah blah, right? So, not a
one-sizefits-all answer here, but pay
attention to those things. So, overall,
exercise wins. And this has been again
documented so many times, I can't even
count. Next one on that stop is breath
work. Remember earlier when you exercise
more CO2, so you breathe more. So, when
you start thinking about it, what is
structured breath work doing? It's kind
of like manipulating a little bit of a
lower level amount of
exercise. It makes sense. The same
physiology happens. The same basic
benefits. It's really
consistent. The framework we use to
think about it is in three basic steps.
If we're going to implement a specific
breathing protocol for somebody, here's
how we do it. Again, for these
particular purposes. Number one, before
we actually put somebody on a breathing
program, we reduce arousal. I said this
a while ago now, but this is actually
step number one. Before you have to go
through this uh meditation or
intentional breath work
protocol, we just got to reduce the
sensory input. We have seen this a lot.
Go for a walk in nature, no podcast, no
music, not as much time. Don't you can't
wake up in the morning, immediately go
to your heavy metal music, work for 15
hours, come home, answer emails, and
then fall asleep. You can because you
burn a lot of energy. You're going to be
tired, but that's going to keep you in a
pretty high state of arousal. So, I'm
telling you right now, if you want to do
breath work, you're into it. Cool. We've
had a lot of people who just don't like
it. I'm be totally can with you. I'm not
the biggest fan myself personally.
always feels good, always works, but
it's not like on my high list of things
I enjoy doing every day. And so, I would
rather just be like, man, I need some
recovery. It's easier for me to just
reduce physical arousal. Give me some
more quiet time. No more sensory input
for the day. That'll take care of most
of it. If that's not enough, the next
step we go to is more time doing nasal
only
breathing. Close your mouth. Breathe
through your nose. Whether this means
you tape your mouth closed while you're
working or you go for a walk and you're
breathing only through your nose or
you're doing some or all or any portion
of your exercise with nasal only
breathing. I don't really care. It
activates the diaphragm more. It tends
to on itself slow respiratory rate down
because you can't move air like you can.
You will notice hyperventilation through
your nose when you won't necessarily
notice hyperventilation through your
mouth. You'll feel that. You'll hear
that. that that would be very different
than it coming through your
mouth. And we also know that nasal
breathing is more parasympathetic on
itself. So by doing that reducing
arousal and then forcing people into
some nasal only breathing time, this
basically takes care of all of our
problems. If you like or want to still
need to do more things past that, at
that point we will instill a specific
breath work protocol and it could look a
bunch of different ways. But again, here
are some samples intuitively here. Just
make your breath do what you want to
feel like. What's that mean? Let's say
you're trying to go up more energy.
you're feeling lethargic or lack of
motivation and you're
down and you're not breathing very much
and everything heart rate's low and
energy is low. Think about it. What
would your breath look like if you were
at a high energy state and then do that.
Force your breath to do something. And
as I talked about earlier, your
physiology will respond to match it.
This is hyperventilation. Breathe more.
Any of you have ever done
hyperventilation breath work? You'll
know within a few seconds tingling in
your arms, you might start sweating,
temperature goes up really acutely. So,
just do that. Just hyperventilate. If
you're in the opposite and you're trying
to come down, just don't breathe as
much. Tons of protocols. Yeah, extended
exhales. Sure, sure, sure, sure. But the
basic concept is slow your breath work
down. That's as complicated as it has to
be. If you want individual protocols,
cool, fine, got them. But that is the
top line strategy here. Most of the
research and most practitioners who are
effective at this are going to use a
combination within one protocol. So
you're going to do not just only
extended exhales, not just slowing your
your breath rate down, not just speeding
it up, but you're going to use a
combination to develop that hormonic
stressor. So if you want to truly
downregulate, you can just simply slow
your breathing down. But actually within
one session, a combination of slower and
faster and slower and
faster will lead to that hormetic
response. And if you finish, especially
on low, it's been our experience and and
the research would support this, you're
going to often times see more of a
parasympathetic response than if you
were to just do parasympathetic alone.
So most of the time we're looking for a
combination of up and down for the same
reasons that we talked about with
exercise. In other words, conflicts of
interest here. I am a board member no
pay here for a nonprofit called the
Health and Human Performance Foundation.
I've been a part of this group for many
years. I was one of the founding
members. I'm bringing that up because
that group led by Tanya Bentley recently
published a phenomenal review article.
We'll link it in the show notes, but I
want to share with you what they found.
They were looking directly at the
relationship between breath work for
stress and anxiety. What do we know in
that review? They found I think 72
papers and something like 75 or
80% of the papers found that the breath
work helped. So just on its surface if
we want to say like does breath work
actually help for anxiety and stress I
think pretty clearly the vast majority
of the time it does. But what was really
interesting that Tanya did there is she
started breaking down the papers and
saying,"Well, what was true among the
papers that worked and what was true
among the papers that didn't?" And can
we glean anything from that? And the
answer was yes. So here we go. There
were a handful of things, in fact, five
things specifically that were common
among all those papers that showed it
worked. And here they are. Number one,
they avoided fast only breathing
practices. I know these are very
popular. People love the the max
inhalation exhalation stuff. They like
hyperventilation breathing. If your goal
is to try to reduce stress and anxiety
chronically, pretty clear evidence at
this point that alone will not do it.
Doesn't mean you can't hyperventilate,
doesn't mean it can't be part of your
practice. But if your only practice is
chronic hyperventilate or consistent
hyperventilation, probably not going to
be effective for reducing your stress
and anxiety long term. Number two, the
breath practice needs to be longer than
five minutes. Number three, generally
needs to be humang guided. So people
that do it by themselves initially
probably not the best strategy. Whether
you're physically in a room with
somebody, that doesn't seem to matter,
but you need to have somebody coaching
you through something at some point,
especially initially. Number
four, it takes multiple sessions per
week. You can't do this once in a while.
You can do it and feel that acute
effect, but it won't have that carryover
chronic benefit. Number
five, there need to be a little bit more
of longer term
practices. This is that four to six to
eight week thing. So, if we were to
recap that, if you're using
non-exclusively hyperventilation, you're
doing it more than five minutes, ideally
multiple times per day, someone that
knows what they're doing, has designed
it, and you're giving yourself four to
five, six
weeks, you got about a 70 to 80% chance
that it will meaningfully and clinically
improve your anxiety and your stress.
That's some framework for breath
protocols should work.
Most of that will take care of HRV, CO2
tolerance, resting heart rate, and
respiratory rate. The next big category
I want to talk about are what are called
BOF feedback mechanisms. There's a lot
of things here, tons of research. I've
actually been tinkering with this stuff
for probably 15 years or so at this
point. I want to categorize them for
today's conversation into two main
areas. One what I'll call internal and
the other that are called external. So
the internal ones are when you're trying
to have that inter interosception.
You're trying to pay attention to your
heart rate and I'm intentionally telling
you to slow your breathing down. So
that's an internal focus. External is
when you're actually watching your
physiology on some screen and you're
just trying to make that thing improve.
So I'm not telling you how to do it. I'm
telling you what I want the response to
be and you're using that direct visual
feedback to make alterations. Both are
great. They're a little bit different
and there's a lot of tools within them.
So, getting us started with a handful
that I'll call
internals and these ones are free or
close to it. The very first one is any
sort of hypoxic exposure. I've talked
about that earlier. Hold your breath,
the Volvo maneuver, anything like that.
This will give you an acute change and
I'll absolutely reset you. It will
change your subjective feeling by simply
holding your breath. If you want to cue
that to some physical exercise like the
balsa or you want to do jumping jacks or
push-ups or something, you'd be
surprised, but a very short burst of
holding your breath combined with
physical activity for a couple of
seconds can change perception pretty
immediately. And I'm calling this BOF
feedback because you're going to feel
it. You're going to do it. I'm telling
you to do something to your body. Ones
that are more chronic though, which is
what we're trying to get into now,
there's a cascade of them. One that
we've used a lot is actually uh a
meditation app, if you will, called
Waking Up. This is by Sam Harris. There
are plenty of ways to
learn of meditation. There are many
different strategies for it, but I'm
highlighting this one because we've used
it a lot as well as because it is a it
is a progressive system. So, you can
kind of take it, follow the course, and
if you don't know anything about
meditation, the lessons are pretty
simple and small, and it kind of walks
you through it. I've personally been
paying for Waking Up for many years.
We've given it to lots of clients plenty
of times, but I've only recently learned
you can try it for free for 30 days by
going to
wakingup.com/huberman. That's my friend
Dr. Andrew Huberman's uh sponsor to his
podcast over there. So, you can try it
all there and I hope you enjoy it. It's
it's truly phenomenal. We've used it a
lot. And why again I'm saying that is we
maybe sometimes someone's done breath
work or they won't do breath work or
they're not interested in meditation. We
can just send them that say hey this is
the only thing we're going to ask you to
do and they can kind of get hooked on a
little bit. They can gify it. They can
get
there just focusing on paying attention
to their breath which is effectively
what Sam is doing in that
course. It's bio feedback. They have no
connection with their breath. They don't
understand what's going on. They're
learning to connect to their breath and
it makes a big difference. That's why
that's in BOF feedback. Another super
simple one is what Brian McKenzie calls
gear one walking. So you're going to
walk 30 minutes, 45 minutes. We have one
client who we have walking almost two
hours a day like this. And why we're
calling it BOF feedback here is you're
breathing through your nose, but you're
breathing at a very specific and
intentional breath rate. Two second
inhale, two second exhale. That's a 4
second rhythm. Why that matters is four
multiplied by 15 is 60. That's 15
breaths per minute, right? As I said
earlier, 15 is kind of that respiratory
line where we start to be concerned. If
you're sleeping and you're breathing 15
breaths per minute, we think that's a
little bit high. But if you're walking,
15 breaths per minute is appropriate. So
in doing this, what we're trying to do
is match an appropriate breath rate with
an appropriate caloric expenditure.
We're not having you do sprints or
you're running where your heart rate's
really, really high and you're under
breathing. We're trying to retrain your
baseline of saying this is what 15
should feel like. Now, when you go back
and sleep, bring it down to 10 or 12 or
wherever the case is. So, it's a very
intentional two in two out. It feels
very, very weird. It's nasal only. You
can't listen to a podcast. You can't
take work emails when you're this. You
have to be in that space and you got to
spend some time there. But it is quite
effective. Third one here we'll talk
about is the cold exposure. Now what I
didn't say earlier is how you can use
cold exposure for bio feedback and
retraining things like respiratory rate.
Common one we have used many many times
get in your cold whether this is your
shower or your bath or whatever you're
doing. I'll give you the first say one
to three breath cycles to kind of calm
yourself down. And then past that we're
not sitting in here for a particular
amount of time.
What we're trying to do is take 10
breaths under
control. We are using the cold to
regulate breath. We are learning
resilience. I put you in a very
physiological and psychological
stressful situation. Your hormones, your
adrenaline, your heart rate will be
flying up. And I'm asking you to control
them despite the fact that they are
wanting to go up. That is exactly how
you build stress inoculation. That's
walking you up to that line of low back
pain, but not pushing you over the edge.
You're not scared. You can get out
anytime. There's no danger here. But
your body will be screaming at you that
this is a all those things. But you know
it's not. You might panic. You might do
a bunch of different things. Fine. Get
out. No problem. That's the game we're
practicing. Just like Dr. Harris in
waking up. The practice is not how much
focus you can have on your breath. The
practice is when you lose focus, can you
bring it back. Same thing here. We're
using the cold to intentionally put you
out of control. And then we're saying,
can you practice regaining control?
That's all we're doing. Now, the things
I just mentioned I call bio feedback,
but they're not the true scientific
definition of that. what we're really
getting into this field is stuff more
specific to HRV based bio feedbacks and
so we'll we'll cover those things right
now a couple examples many years ago I
had a colleague who was actually a
sports psychologist who used BOF
feedback this way he would put athletes
in front of a computer screen and he
would have I think an electrode attached
to their ear um that was measuring
things in a and a pulse oximter and they
would look at a screen and it was say a
picture of a landscape or maybe kids
playing at a park and it was all in
black and white and he would not tell
them anything but he would simply say
make that picture turn into color and
they're staring at a screen they're like
what and then all a sudden the screen
would start filling in color and then it
would go away back to black white and it
would take people a while but once they
realized oh wow when I bring my heart
rate down I get more colors on the
screen and so they would bring their
heart rate down and the colors would
start filling in then we get excited and
then the colors would go away and so
they're not paying paying attention.
He's not telling them, "Bring your heart
rate down, stop breathing as much,
exhale, extended exhales." He's asking
for an external solution and they are
figuring out internally how to get
there. Awesome. Awesome. And then
there's lots of different tools and
technologies for that. But an awesome
way of developing bio feedback that way.
Really simple examples of stuff we've
used for many years are things like a
weight belt. Yeah. 20 bucks on Amazon.
You put this strap around your stomach
and you can actually see increased
propriception in your core muscles. Lots
of research on this. If you take a
weight belt and you cinch it down
really, really tight and you go to lift
your
weights, there's been many studies show
a reduction in core strength in response
to that. You make it so tight, think of
it this way, the core muscles turn off.
They don't have to do their work because
the belt's doing it. That said, if you
put the belt on just kind of a little
bit, you can see increases in core
strength. Why? Because you gives you a
little bit of a tactile feedback. You
know that you're not pressing hard with
your core. You know, you're not
activating in all spots because you can
feel the belt pressing back up against
it when you're contracting hard. So,
because of that, it gives somebody a bio
feedback reminder, a tactile feedback.
Keep your core engaged. Keep your core
engaged. And so, by keeping it engaged
more often, you get more of a training
effect. Same exact principle can be
applied here. You can put people through
a specific breath protocol or you can
put a weight belt on them. Put a bigger
one. Put a a lot of the ones we'll use
are like fat burning stomach belts. You
know the ones you put on you're like
plastic on them and they're there to
help people think they're going to have
a six-pack. But what what it's just
doing is giving you that feedback. You
don't necessarily have to give them a
program. You can just say, "Hey, wear
this for 20 minutes. Wear this for a
couple of hours." you'll start to feel,
man, I'm not breathing through my core.
I'm breathing through my shoulders. I'm
breathing through my neck. So, number
one, we're starting to make improvement
and progress in breathing
mechanics. It also generally tends to
slow people's breath rate down because
you feel you'll
hear that belt crunching and moving and
going back and forth and you're like,
geez, that's happened a lot. And you
tend to just slow it down. Simple BOF
feedback, easy solutions, no complicated
schemes at all, very effective. For
those of you that want more structure
and specific protocols to follow, this
last one will get you really excited.
There's a whole bunch of research on
what's called resonant breathing. This
is HRV, BOF feedback resonance. There's
lots of different terms for it, but if
you Google that phrase, this will what
will come up. same goal, trying to give
you more ability to recognize and
control your
HRV. Recent meta analysis found very
positive benefits for self-reported
stress and anxiety. Other papers have
looked at this and found positive
benefits for cognitive function and
depression. It has the same basic
prescription of the other breath work.
You probably got to do it for about 20
minutes per day. Takes four or five
weeks, ideally morning and night.
morning and night rather and so that
stuff is fixed but what is specific
about this it's really really clever a
lot of the research here came from a guy
named Paul Layer L E Her I believe out
of
Ruters in general this resonance is
supposed to be consistent throughout
life now I don't know if more research
comes out that that'll change but that
is as far as we understand it it seems
to be about the same so this resonance
frequency is something internal to you
in your respiratory rate starts to match
up with your HRV and your heart rate.
Like, what? What? Here's what I mean.
It's really, really clever stuff. This
is like really fascinating
research. I use that optimal HRV app I
told you earlier. It's five bucks a
month. The studies oftentimes will use
another app called Paste Breathing. That
is just simply an app that helps you
watch the app and breathe in and out at
the right time. All right. So on that
optimal HRV app, you can do this test
that I'm about to take you through as
well as the training. It's why I like it
so much. So I can send people that polar
strap. I can send them this app, say, do
this resonance test and then our
training program is based upon the
results of this particular test. It's
telling you how long to inhale and
exhale. Remember earlier where I've said
kind of like five in, five out or six
in, six out is a good starting place.
That's true. But the individual
responses to people is different and
this is a phenomenal way to figure out
which cadence is best for you. The test
takes about 12 minutes and effectively
what happens is you start at a breath
rate of about seven breaths per minute.
Now depending on the study you'll find
most will actually start you at about 6
and a half. I think the optimal HRV if I
remember correctly starts you at six and
a half and then some have gone all the
way down to as low as three breaths per
minute. Most are going to start you at
like six and a half breaths per minute
and drop you to four or so breaths per
minute. Here's exactly what I'm talking
about. You breathe for two minutes at
this specific cadence. Let's say 6 and a
half seconds in, 6 and 1/2 seconds out.
And you do that for a total of two
minutes. While you're doing that, it's
measuring your HRV. Okay? What it's
trying to identify is when your HRV gets
the
highest. So you're breathing in and out
at seven at six and a half breaths per
minute and then you go from 6 and a half
to six. So every two minutes you lower
your breathing rate by half a breath per
minute. Now for some people when they go
from six and a half to six their HRV
goes down and some people it goes up and
then you go from six to five and a half
to five.
all the way down. Like I said, someone
as three. At some point in that
spectrum, your HRV will be its
highest. Where that lands is totally
dependent upon the person. So, let's say
we do the test and my optimal HRV
happens at six breaths per minute and
yours happens at
four. That's that's called our resonance
frequency. I now know you will get the
highest HRV right now when you breathe
at four breaths per minute. So then
you're going to spend more time
breathing at four breaths per minute
where I'm going to do six. That make
sense, right? So we're looking at how
can I actually
optimize my inhalation exhalation
strategy to get the highest impact on my
HRV? Well, it turns out this strategy is
highly
effective. I'll go over more of those
details here in one moment.
When we're defining higher HRV, it's
really actually important that the
highest HRV score like you're going to
see on your wearables is not what we're
necessarily talking about here. That
there's three criteria that are used to
determine best HRV score. And that yeah,
that RMSS thing is is the lowest one.
Highest on this is what's called low
frequency power. This is another way of
kind of defining and measuring your
veagal nerve power. This is parameter.
This is the thing we're optimizing for
rather than that actual HRV
score. Another really interesting one is
looking at your HRV amplitude. I've
talked about that before. It's the
difference between kind of your maximum
heart rate and your minimum heart rate
in one breath
cycle. Remember, when you breathe in,
heart rate goes up. When you breathe
out, it goes down. And so, let's say
when you took a breath in, you went to
80. And you took a breath out and it
went to 40. 80 minus 40 is 40. So
therefore your amplitude is 40. One
thing that you'll see is people that are
really well trained physically have a
really big amplitude. People can go like
a a
welltrained individual, cardiovascularly
fit individual might have a resting
heart rate of 40 and they might jump
from 40 to like 90. So that amplitude
would be 50. Where someone who's not
very physically fit might go from 60 to
70. Their amplitude is 10.
I know I'm throwing a lot of numbers and
most of you are listening so that's hard
to follow along but just the amplitude
the difference your ability of your
heart rate to go from really high to
really low within one breath cycle is a
positive thing that is an indicative of
a really really um uh resilient nervous
system and remember from the very
beginning that's what we're talking
about today the HV score itself again
cool it's on there but it's the bottom
list so that's what we're optimizing for
and I needed to draw that little
technical detail out there because I
wanted to make sure that it's landing so
deeply in your brain that we're trying
to go after that resilience, not the
score. And those other two measures,
that frequency, power, and that heart
rate amplitude are the things that are
more important than just that HRV score.
So, more to be said about the resonant
breathing thing, but it's just really
phenomenal area uh that we love. Um I
wish I had something to do with those
companies. I don't. Uh but they're just
phenomenal products. So, I wanted to
make sure you had some specific example
of something you could go try that I
personally used and that I like. Last
thing I wanted to mention, and this is
what some of you might deem to be
outrageous, but again, full disclosure
here, I have one of these things. I
don't have anything to do with the
company, but this is something that I'm
seeing pop up a lot. I was just
traveling around the country recently
and saw a bunch of different
professional and other groups using it.
I have one at my home and this is a
chair called the Shift Wave. It is
$10,000, but it is phenomenal. You lay
in this chair. It has haptic feedback,
so it will vibrate. It has sensory
control, what you're seeing, what you're
hearing. It has a whole bunch of
programs. It will directly measure your
heart rate and HRV. And you can do
guided bio feedback through again
movement, through uh light and sound,
and a bunch of different strategies.
I've used it a bunch. Um, we use it a
lot with again special groups of
individuals and it's been really
impressive. So, those of you that just
want to know what the best in the world
are doing behind the scenes. I can't say
that everyone's doing it, but I know
some are and it is really pretty
awesome. And so, there you go. Check out
the Shift Wave chair if you'd like. If
that is completely ridiculous, you're
like, $10,000 for a chair? I totally get
it. And so, we'll move on to our last
couple of things that I just couldn't
leave off the table. No good podcast can
be done without talking briefly, and I
do mean very briefly, about supplements.
First and foremost, what we're talking
about here mostly are acute benefits.
Take caffeine, take a stimulant, you're
going to change sympathetic drive, and
you all know that. But what's more
interesting, and I dove into a lot of,
was what do we know about chronic
benefits? So, if you're in that hole and
HRV is way down for a long time, can
supplements do much to bring you out of
that hole and and bring that HRV back
up, bring that respiratory rate down or
however we're defining autonomic
control. The short answer is not really.
Well, maybe they can, but there's not a
lot of evidence to support that. Closest
thing I found was there was actually
several review articles and meta
analyses on
omega-3s. uh benefit doesn't seem to be
huge. We know a lot of positive benefits
omega-3s, but this doesn't seem to be a
massive one, but there's some indication
that there's some help here. So, that
was pretty cool. Other ones that we'll
see, uh I actually found a study on
watermelon juice. Now, this may surprise
you, but people don't realize the
citrine and arginine, the nitric oxide
capacity in in watermelons is is pretty
high. So, there's a pretty cool study.
They actually did it in combination with
like an oral glucose tolerance test. And
what they effectively found was it
doesn't improve HRV, but what it does do
is it blunts the HRV response when you
dose them with something that should
normally compromise it. It's stress
inoculation. In fact, if you look at
other things like
ashwagandha, very similar types of
research. So, it's not that these things
will take your resting HRV and make it
get better, but what it will do is it
helps you not be as responsive to a
stressful stimuli. That is the true
benefit. So, whether this is
highintensity exercise or a
psychological stressor, things like
watermelon juice or ashwagandha may
blunt how much of a impact those things
make on you. So, kind of stress
inoculators, if you will, but they're
not really recovering you from that
hole, but worthy of mention nonetheless.
A final one that I thought worthy of
talking about was actually a review
article on human studies that found an
association between low vitamin D and
B12 and low HRV. This was not a
randomized control trial. This was not
an intervention study, but it was
interesting nonetheless. So, I'll keep
my eye out for more work in this area.
Maybe we'll see that maybe if you take
people who are low and again in vitamin
D and B12, you will actually see a
chronic improvement in HRV over time.
Maybe you won't. Not sure. I'd be
willing to bet if you take and just give
people who are normal in vitamin D and
B12, those supplements, it probably
won't do much, but we'll have to wait
and see how the data pan out. So, we've
covered a lot of ground today. I think
we should finish on a little bit of a
wrap-up.
want to keep this stuff in proper
context. Remember that hormesis. We want
to stimulate but we don't want to
annihilate. You want to touch the
boundaries. You want to desensitize but
we don't want to push people so far into
an area where it actually creates a
greater stress response, a greater
protective mechanism. Small bump in
uncomfortableness gives you a nice
rebound. That's what we're looking for.
But a huge trauma is not helpful or
potentially even sends us backwards.
There are a couple of types of people in
this world in this regard. I I call them
big feelers. People that have that high
introsception. They pay attention to
themselves too much and they cause
themselves way too much stress because
they're hyperfocused on every little
thing. In that case, maybe don't use
that technology. Use more the feeling
type of stuff or don't do anything. Pull
them off of of a lot of these things.
Then you have the dull knives is what I
call them. People that just have no
contact with their body whatsoever.
Maybe you want to use more of these
technological solutions to get more
calibrated and more aware. Other big
conclusion we talked about is
overall the first step is just reducing
arousal. This is a free thing you can
do. It's probably going to have multiple
benefits across multiple areas of your
life. And so before we start worrying
about specific protocols or supplements
or anything like that, let's just start
by reducing our overall stress cup.
Number three, find things that work best
for you. This is fill your recovery cup.
This is something I haven't said yet,
but it's really what I've been getting
at the whole time. It's not enough
always to just reduce stimuli. Sometimes
you got to actively
recover. Most people don't think about
actively recovering until they
desperately need it. So, not being
stressed is not the same as fully
recovered. Spend time figuring out what
hits it for you. I know some of the
things that land for me and they're not
the same for my wife. They're not the
same for my family members or some of
the athletes I work with. What really
fills your recovery bucket up. Spend
time tinkering with that and then use it
honestly quite often and as much as you
possibly can. Final thing I'll say here
is don't expect those acute solutions.
Whether it's the supplements or the
thermal immersions or the motivational
quote or the music, don't expect those
acute things to fix chronic problems,
right? When you use the chronic problem
solution stuff, probably looking at more
than five minutes a day, ideally every
day, if not multiple times a day, at
least for the first four to six weeks.
Past that, you can back it down. maybe
even as little as just a couple of times
per week and you should be in a pretty
good spot. Want to finish up by giving
some thank yous as people have mentioned
several times now. Thank you Dr. Jay
Wows. Jay, you were phenomenal. You were
so helpful here. Uh we had a lot of
conversations and I deeply appreciate
your help
there. Uh Jill Miller I mentioned and
your book body by breath covered a lot
of these concepts. It was also
incredibly helpful. Emily and Brian at
Shift Adapt and then somebody else,
Martin McFilly, who I haven't had a
chance to speak about yet, but has done
a lot of great work in this area. So,
all you people, thank you so much for
your help. I appreciate all of you for
listening. I hope you have some new
skills, some new things to try, some
direct tools. Some may be more
interesting to a few of you, others may
be uh less so, but either way, I would
really love to hear feedback.
which ones did you like? Which ones have
you had different experiences with? And
if any of you do take the time to go try
something, uh comments on YouTube would
be a great place to fill me in on on
what worked, what didn't, and any other
feedback you have. Thank you so much,
and I look forward to doing it again.
Thank you for joining for today's
episode. My goal, as always, is to share
exciting scientific insights that help
you perform at your best. If the show
resonates with you and you want to help
ensure this information remains free and
accessible to anyone in the world, there
are a few ways that you can support.
First, you can subscribe to the show on
YouTube, Spotify, and Apple. And on
Apple and Spotify, you can leave us up
to a five-star review. Subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot. Also, please check out our
sponsors. The show would not exist
without them and their exceptional
products and services. Finally, you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it. If you have
any content questions or suggestions,
please put those in the comments section
on YouTube. I really do try my best to
read them all and to see what you have
to say. I use my Instagram and
ex-profiles also exclusively for
scientific communication. So, those are
great places to follow along for more
learning. My handle is Dr. Andy Galpin
on both platforms. We also have an email
newsletter that distills all of our
episodes in the most actionable
takeaways. We have newsletters on how to
improve fitness in V2 max, how to build
muscle and strength, and much more. To
subscribe to the newsletter, just go to
performpodcast.com and click newsletter.
It's completely free and we do not share
your email with anybody. Thank you for
listening and never forget in the famous
words of Bill Bowererman, if you have a
body, you are an athlete.